<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most exact and true relation, extracted out of the registers of the acts, ordinances, and publick instruments. Wheerby [sic] those passages are laid open, which hapned since the pacification made at Roschilt, on the 26. of Febr. 1657/8. between the most serene princes, the kings of Denmark and Norway, and the King of Sweden; as also, since the immediately ensuing treaties, at Coppenhaghen, and elsewhere, between the Danish commissioners, and the Sweedish ambassadors ... the Swedes infringing the said peace and treaties ... without any cause ... did on the 9th of August of the same year, lay siege unto the the [sic] kingly residency of Coppenhaghen, and to the Castle of Cronenberg, both by sea and land. Translated out of the Danish, and High Dutch copies, printed at Coppenhaghen. Together with a letter written from Hamborough, by an impartial hand. Demonstrating the several mistakes, and sinister allegations, in the Swedish relation ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89355</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866836</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119122</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248499724</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E977_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207808</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866836</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866836e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89355)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 145:E977[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most exact and true relation, extracted out of the registers of the acts, ordinances, and publick instruments. Wheerby [sic] those passages are laid open, which hapned since the pacification made at Roschilt, on the 26. of Febr. 1657/8. between the most serene princes, the kings of Denmark and Norway, and the King of Sweden; as also, since the immediately ensuing treaties, at Coppenhaghen, and elsewhere, between the Danish commissioners, and the Sweedish ambassadors ... the Swedes infringing the said peace and treaties ... without any cause ... did on the 9th of August of the same year, lay siege unto the the [sic] kingly residency of Coppenhaghen, and to the Castle of Cronenberg, both by sea and land. Translated out of the Danish, and High Dutch copies, printed at Coppenhaghen. Together with a letter written from Hamborough, by an impartial hand. Demonstrating the several mistakes, and sinister allegations, in the Swedish relation ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18, 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.C. for John Crooke, at the signe of the ship, in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An exact relation of the transactions &amp; proceedings between the kings of Denmark and Sweden", with caption title, begins new pagination sequence.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dano-Swedish Wars, 1657-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Denmark --  History --  Frederick III, 1648-1670 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Norway --  History --  Frederick III, 1648-1670 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Swenen --  History --  Charles X Gustavus, 1654-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119122:1"/>
            <p>A most Exact and True RELATION, EXTRACTED Out of the REGISTERS of the ACTS, ORDINANCES, and Publick INSTRUMENTS. Wheerby those <hi>Passages</hi> are laid open, which hapned since the <hi>Pacification</hi> made at <hi>Roschilt,</hi> on the 26. of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1657/8. between the <hi>most Serene Princes,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> and the King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> AS ALSO, Since the immediately ensuing <hi>Treaties,</hi> at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> and the else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, between the <hi>Danish Commissioners,</hi> and the <hi>Sweedish Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors. MANIFESTING</hi> To the whole World, That the <hi>Swedes infringing</hi> the said <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> without any <hi>preceading Denuntiation of War,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Cause,</hi> or <hi>Reason</hi> given them, did on the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>August</hi> of the same Year, lay Siege unto the the <hi>Kingly Residency of Coppenhaghen,</hi> and to the Castle of <hi>Cronenberg,</hi> both by Sea and Land. <hi>Translated out of the</hi> Danish, <hi>and</hi> High Dutch Copies, <hi>Printed at</hi> Coppenhaghen. TOGETHER WITH A LETTER written from HAMBOROUGH, By an Impartial Hand. <hi>Demonstrating</hi> The several <hi>Mistakes,</hi> and <hi>Sinister Allegations,</hi> in the <hi>Swedish Relation;</hi> meerly contrived to <hi>palliate</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Swedens</hi> unjust Attempts, and unanswerable proceedings against his Neghbour POTENTATES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>John Crooke,</hi> at the Signe of the Ship, in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119122:2"/>
            <head>Advertisment to the Reader.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, we give you a true Relation of what hath passed between the <hi>two Northern Kings,</hi> since the <hi>Treaty of Pacification at Rotshild, in February last,</hi> 1657/8 as it was Printed in <hi>the Danish, and High Dutch Languages, by the</hi> Order of the <hi>King,</hi> and the approbation of the <hi>Senatators of the Kingdome of Denmark,</hi> who acknowledg it, to be theirs. This will doubtlesse meet with a better admittance, and credit then one which hath been formerly published, <hi>on the behalf of the Swedes,</hi> we know not by whom, only in the <hi>English tongue,</hi> &amp; questtionless by a mercinary Pen, which sticketh not to write any thing, right, or wronge, truth, or untruth, so it may but serve turne, to inveagle this Nation: which he thinks to delude by his smooth expressions: the rather because they live re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the place where these transactions have passed, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, we might persawde our selves, that this Relation will be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, to discover the truth to those that read it, without parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality on either side. Yet for the Readers better satisfaction, we have prefixed a Letter written by an impartiall hand from Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow, which will afforde much light to those, who shall give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the trouble to read the <hi>Swedish Paper,</hi> and to compare the one Relation, with the other: Mean while we shall commend you to the Protection of the Almighty, not doubting, but you will wish a good success to that party, which you will finde to have justice on its side.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119122:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER Writen from HAMBOROUGH, BY AN IMPARTIAL HAND, To a Friend at <hi>LONDON.</hi> Whereby the several Mistakes, and Sinister Allegations, in the Swedish Relation, Printed at <hi>London,</hi> are laid open, and published for the Satisfaction of such as desire to be rightly informed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Letter of the third of <hi>Decembr.</hi> and withall the Book entituled, <hi>A true Relation of the Reasons which necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated His Majestie of Sweden to continue the War with Denmark:</hi> And whereas we that live in this Cittie, neerer to the Place which is the <hi>Bloody Theatre of Mars,</hi> then you do, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver till this very day hear of any such thing, as a Reason, whereby his said Majesty was moved to undertake this Second Expedition, against that already sufficiently afflicted Kingdom of Denmark; I supposed, that perhaps Kings, like unto great Figures in Tapestry, were best observed at a Distance; and their Actions best considered by those that are remote; who for the most part judge of them more sincerely, and freely, as being less swayed by Partiality. For I could not imagine, that it was a <hi>Work published by the Swedish Party,</hi> who assuredly would have divulged it, either in their own Language or in Latin, before it should have apeared in English. But to be free with you, my opinion was, that <hi>His Majestie</hi> would not at all have published his reasons in Print, contenting himself with the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereon made, by the <hi>Earl of Slippenbagh his Commissioner,</hi> to the <hi>Danish
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119122:3"/> Ambassadors</hi> before <hi>Coppenhaguen,</hi> to wit, <hi>that his Majesties inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to Master the Citties, and strong places, as well as be had the Country; which is as much as to say, I have a minde to be the sole Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne of the</hi> 3 <hi>Northren Kingdomes.</hi> Or if his Majestie would so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniously have declared his minde to all the world. I thought it might have been done in a lesse volume; for most men knew it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and as to those that were ignorant thereof, they needed but to call to minde what expeditions <hi>the King of Sweden</hi> hath undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en since he came to the Crown; and so little Rethorick would have served turn, to perswade them thereunto. These and such like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, unnecessarie to be alledged, made me suppose <hi>an indifferent honest man might have been the Author of the book;</hi> who would have performed what the <hi>Title bespeaketh, To be true in his relation, and to shew what reasons necessitated the King of Sweden, to continue the Warr: as well as the truth, that the warr was continued,</hi> and might with as much truth have affirmed, <hi>that the peace concluded at Roschilt was nothing less then a peace, or rather nothing else save a stratagem of war, whereby the Swedes have gotten into their power the Provinces of Shonen, Bleking, Halland, and a great part of Norway, together with all the strong places of the same without the losse of one single man,</hi> which all the <hi>power of Sweden,</hi> would have found very difficult to have compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, by force of arms, in many years.</p>
            <p>And perceiving by the Title, <hi>that the King of Sweden was necessitated to continue the war against Denmark.</hi> I was the more earnest to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use the book, hoping in the first place, to have found the <hi>reason of this necessitated second invasion, to have been the Austrian, Polonian, and Brandenburgesh forces uniting themselves into a body of an army, so considerable, as that his Majestie had reason to conceive himself too weak to fight them with advantage, or without endangering his own forces,</hi> which, <hi>rebus sic stantibus, might yet be sufficient to oppresse the King of Denmark, unarmed, and unawares: whose Kingdomes consisting in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slands, might the better shelter him, and his army, by reason the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said forces, could not probably well attempt them there; nor could the World term it a retreat, whil'st thereby his Majestie might have gained the whole Kingdome of Denmark. And by taking but</hi> 40, <hi>or</hi> 50 <hi>Pr. Ct. toll in the sound, of those that traffick in the Baltick Sea, as his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119122:3"/> King Gustavus Adolphus had formerly done at the Pillow, in the Years two and three and thirty: might haue raised such a vast summe of money, as would have enabled him to overrune the rest of his Neighbours, in whose Countreys, his all destroying Army, had not as yet exercised their unheard of Cruelties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I no sooner turned the leaf, and cast my eye upon the work (whose inscription had been so pleasing to me) when I found my self very much deceived in my expectations, meeting with nothing lesse then what the title promised; <hi>Never having beheld a Publik Inteligencer, more abounding in lyes, nonsence, contradictions, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, such as in your parts you now terme, Astrologicall Predictions; belching out Slanders, and invectives, against a King and Kingdome; then this pretended true relation doth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Werefore, give me leave, Sir to exammine some partes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, And in the first place <hi>o observe, with how little truth, and reason the Author accuses the King, and Kingdome of Denmark, for having injuriously provocked the King of Sweden; and whether or no the Danes did perfideously make an irruption into the Swedish territories, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cause given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which that it may the more evidently appear to be <hi>false,</hi> to your self, and to such as you shall find not sufficiently informed, of the trurh of these proceedings, I shall in a percursory way, hint unto you the several breaches of the articles of former Treaties, by the Swedes, on which no satisfaction being obtained, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so often pressed, and earnestly demanded; might justly move his <hi>Majestie of Denmark,</hi> to seek that reparation, by force of armes, which was denyed him, and his Ministers, by way of amicable treaties, and will consequently prove, <hi>that his Majestie of Denmarks taking up of armes against the Swedes, was on a just necessity, and there fore no injurious provocation; persidious Irruption, nor groundlesse at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These following articles, of the Treatyes of <hi>Bremsbroe, Munster,</hi> and <hi>Stetin,</hi> were infringed by the Swedes, If you observe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by vertue of the 8 article of the treaty of peace conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between the two Crowns of <hi>Denmark, and Sweden, at Bremsbroe,</hi> the Arch-Bishop of Bremen (now King of Denmark) being compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119122:4"/> therein, was to treate with <hi>Sweden,</hi> about the restitution of the <hi>Arch-Bishopprick of Bremen,</hi> which was promised him, but when his <hi>Ambassadors arrived at Stockholm,</hi> they were not only derided and sent away, <hi>re infecta,</hi> but moreover his <hi>Highness the Arch-Bishops place of Residence, the Castle of Bremerverde,</hi> was by the <hi>Swedish forces, under the command of Generall Koningsmark,</hi> besieged, and taken, together with all what was therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it was agreed on, in the 25 article of the said treaty, that all the <hi>Lands in Norway</hi> taken by the <hi>Swedish forces,</hi> should be restored to the <hi>Crown of Denmark,</hi> except <hi>Jempterland, and Heren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> notwithstanding the Swedes till this day, could never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to accomplish this article, by the restoring of the two Parishes <hi>Irn, and Zern,</hi> belonging to <hi>Aggershuse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That his <hi>Majesties tolls in the Sound,</hi> have been defrauded of vast, and eminent summes of money, by the <hi>Swedish Ministers,</hi> residing there, who granted their <hi>Certificates and passes</hi> to every one, of what nation soever, that demanded them, so they would but part with some gratuity to the said <hi>Ministers, and their Servants,</hi> as it hath been proved to them; and can bee Evidenced to all the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That <hi>Corfitz, Ulefelt,</hi> formerly <hi>Rixhof-Master, or Lord High Steward,</hi> and since <hi>a Rebel to his King, and Country,</hi> was not only, kindely received, and honourably entertained in the <hi>Swedish Court</hi> but that moreover, <hi>the Queen Christina of Sweden,</hi> would take upon herself to be a Judge, and oblige his <hi>Majestie of Denmark, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of his Ambassador,</hi> to plead his cause, in her presence against his own undutyfull Subjects; Contrary to the <hi>Treaty of Stetin,</hi> conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Year 1570, as also against that of Bremsbroe, in the year 1645 by the 22. articles.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the <hi>Swedes</hi> have sollicited the Haunce Towns, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with them, in the ruining and destroying of the Commerce of the <hi>Kingdome of Denmarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That they intermedled in the differences arisen between the <hi>King of Denmark,</hi> and his <hi>Kinsman the Duke of Gottorp,</hi> as if they could not have been commposed in an amicable manner, or by the ordinary way of Law, <hi>without their promising him their forces;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they made him neglect his <hi>Majesties freindship,</hi> and such peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119122:4"/> thoughts, as might have conduced to the mutuall good of both parties.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That they began <hi>to dispute the King of Denmark, his undoubted Rights, and Title, unto the Dukedome of Ditmars, and the County of Delmhorst.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. That they Marched with their forces through the <hi>Dukedomes of Holstein, County of Pinnenbergh, and the province of Jutland,</hi> to the great prejudice and detriment of the Inbabitants, without his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties permision, <hi>and contrary to the treaty of peace at Munster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. That the <hi>Inhabitants of the province of Halland,</hi> were by them deprived of their priviledges, contrary to the 27 <hi>Article</hi> of the Treaty of <hi>Bremsebroe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. That the <hi>Lands in the Islands Rugen,</hi> called <hi>Ralsweigh,</hi> and those whom his Majestie had invested therewith, whose <hi>Protector he is</hi> being engaged to maintan them, in their freedomes and priviledges, were neverthelesse burthened by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> with taxes and extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Contrary to the usuall customes, and to their former Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That they observed not the 24 <hi>article</hi> of the afore mentioned <hi>treaty of Bremsbroe,</hi> concerning <hi>Dantzick,</hi> and the liberty of trade between his Majesties Subjects, and that Citty, and that they took some, and Molested others of the <hi>Danish Ships,</hi> going to, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from <hi>Danzick,</hi> befor ever they had any Ships, much lesse a Fleet before that Citty.</p>
            <p>Besides many other grievances, whereon his Majestie never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse endeavoured to obtain satisfaction by fair means, but the <hi>Swedish Resident Durel,</hi> who was then at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing, as it should seem, of those differences, <hi>in lieu of giving satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the King, returned nothing, save threatening Language, broak of his negotiation, and went his wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Judg you therefore, whether any one can be so greata Stranger to these truths, as not to discern, <hi>that the penner of the Swedish pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended true Relation, is an horrid vile Imposture. And whether his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie of Denmark could promise himself any other satisfaction, save such a one as his Father Christian the</hi> 4th <hi>of everlasting memorie, received from them in the Year</hi> 43? <hi>and whether his Majestie had no just cause given
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119122:5"/> him, to betake himself to his armes, not only thereby to obtain satisfaction for the wrongs he had already sustained, but also to defend himself, and his Kingdoms, against those who threa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned to deal far worse by him. And yet for all this his Majestie did not perfideously make use of his Forces, as your writer is pleased to affirm, but declared, and proclaimed an open warr against the King, and Kingdom of Sweden, on their fronteirs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Knowen Maximes of War: Nor did his Majestie of Denmark, under a coulor of Freindship, and on a pretence of embarking his army for Porrussia, or some other place, invade the Territotories of an Allye, with whom he was but newly entred into a Leauge of freindship; Neither did he unawares fall upon a Prince, unto whom Neutrality was first granted, and afterwards sold: Far lesse did he ever attempt, and invade another Kingdome, which begged for peace, having no other cawse so to do, save onely that it was already opprest by severall barbarous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, taking it for granted, to be a sufficient reason and opportunity to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runn, and conquer the same.</hi> Though others have done it, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better deserve such Titles, as your writer bestoweth upon the <hi>King of Denmark, and the Danish Nation, without so much as scrupuling the Unlawfulness of uttering them, against Crowned Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much as to the Title, and injurious Terms of the Book; and for the matters it containeth, though some of them are true, yet you will finde they are alleadged to little or no purpose, or in a wrong sense, as I have already shewed you he did in the very Title: but for the most part, you will finde them to be <hi>meerly false,</hi> as you may easily discover, by reading the <hi>Danish Relation,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving the manifold Contradictions of <hi>his own.</hi> Some points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I intend only to touch upon; for should I go about to canvass them all, I should exceed the form of a Letter.</p>
            <p>In the first place therefore, the Swedish Relator sayeth, <hi>That the whole Kingdom of Denmark, the King, Queen, the rest of the Royal Court, the Senators, and the Nobility, were in a short time reduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his (the King of Swedens) power and mercy;</hi> at such a time when as he had but one strong place in the whole Kingdom, to wit, <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericks Odde;</hi> in lieu whereof the <hi>King of Denmark his Forces in Norway</hi> had taken several strong Holds of his, on the borders of Sweden, 'Tis true, <hi>he had overrun the Danish Islands;</hi> but theforere
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119122:5"/> all was not lost: <hi>and might not the King of Sweden have been driven out of them, as well as he was out of Poland?</hi> where he had also a footing in the Country; besides many considerable places, as <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow, Warshow, Lublin,</hi> and others; in which Kingdom he hath not at present, so much as one foot of ground? no more had he, at that time we speak of, in the <hi>two strongest Provinces of Denmark, Shonen and Blecking:</hi> Neither was the King of Denmark with his Queen, &amp;c. at that time as yet in his power, or at his mercy. Howbeit he as then perhaps, made his reckoning without his Host, as well as he did this last time, when as he promised his people about him, that at <hi>Coppenhaghen</hi> they should finde, both Doars and Windows open to receive them; but when this proved otherwise, <hi>then Coppenhagben was to be taken by force of Arms, and the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, with his whole Royal Progenie, were to be sent Priseners to Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm, with the same Ceremonies, as have since been used in the sending of the Duke of Curland, with his Lady, and Children, to Riga:</hi> But when this would not do neither, <hi>then Coppenhaghen was te be reduced to ashes:</hi> But God be thanked, it hath not been in the Swedish power to effect this neither; whereby you may see how doubtful it was, whether the King, Queen, and the Danish Court, were at that time your Writer alledgeth, in the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> power, and at his mercy; which if it had been so, doubtless he would not have spared them. Thus much I can tell you, that at that very time there were in <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> besides the Citizens, 5000 <hi>horse and foot,</hi> and between 2 <hi>or</hi> 3000 <hi>Seamen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you may object, they were possessed with terrour; 'tis very likely they were so; and do you not think they were so likewise this last time? when as they found the <hi>Swedish Army</hi> before the Gates of the City, and moreover, <hi>a Royal Swedish Fleet</hi> before their harbour, most unexpectedly, at such a time, when as they never drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of an Enemy, untill they saw him at their very Walls? after their Army was partly disbanded, and partly delivered to the Swedes, as well as all the strong places in <hi>Shonen</hi> and <hi>Bleiking,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to agreement; from whence in former times they might have received ayde and assistance, yet when they perceived that none of his Majesties proffers to the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> were accepted, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119122:6"/> that his Resolution was, <hi>To have the strong places in his possession, as well as he had the Country,</hi> they resolved rather to dye with their Swords in their hands, than by their good wills to see the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of their Houses, the violating of their Wives, and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their Children: as it hath been practised by the same Enemy upon their Princes Subjects, in <hi>Holstein</hi> and elsewhere.</p>
            <p>But put the case that those of <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> who during this last Siege, have given sufficient proof of their valour, were such pitifull Creatures, as this Writer, with little reason endeavours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the World, (and the contrary whereof he would have found had he been on the place;) why then dares he be so impudent, as to alledge afterwards, that 8 or 900 of them, (according to his discrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, pitifully cloathed, ill mounted, and men wholly unexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in Warlike affairs,) could resolve to go with an intention to take the King of Swedens person out of that Army, wherewithall he presumed to master the whole City, in such a season of the year, when as, in all probability, his Souldiers could not be very fit for Action, by reason of the excessive cold, unless God, (who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Swedish Tenents, miraculously made them a Bridge of Ice over the Sea) should by another miracle have caused the Sun to skip over five Signs of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> viz. from <hi>Aquarius</hi> to <hi>Leo,</hi> as nimblyas the Swedish army marched from one Island into the other.</p>
            <p>Moreover, your Author doth endeavour to make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> hath no more Conscience to keep his Royal word, and to observe his solemn Treatyes, than we see others have; though by his leave, me thinks he ought to harbour a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all Men, but especially of a Prince, till such t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me as he be able to prove something to the contrary; yet since it is his pleasure, <hi>to rail at Kings as if they were Scullions,</hi> let us I pray, consider how his injurious terms do sute with the structure of his work, For amongst many others of his Invectives he saith, The <hi>Danes</hi> harboured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Designs, artificiall Treacheries, Delayes, and Delusions, and such like terms, which he useth, to make them pass for a kind of subtle People; and yet in another place, he would needs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the World, They have held correspondencyes with the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strians, Poles, Brandenbourghers,</hi> and other Enemies of the King of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119122:6"/>
               <hi>Sweden,</hi> at such a time, when the whole Swedish Army did lye in heir Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, and that <hi>with so little secrecy,</hi> as to give your Author reason to boast, he knows all the particulars thereof: moreover would not you or any man else think the <hi>Danes</hi> to be a very cunning People? should they harbour any such thoughts as your Author ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuses them of? and yet restore ships, deliver men, surrender all their strong places, one after the other, and pay sums of mony to the Swedes, according to the tenor of the Treaty, and nevertheless be minded to break the same Treaty, which must needs have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to their great disadvantage. Certainly there can be no greater madness imagined, than to think that any one would give up his Arms to an Enemy, with an intent to fight with him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Yet to beget some credit to this his as false, as frivilous an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, he forestalls a marching away of part of the <hi>Sweedish Army,</hi> that thereby his pretences might seem to have some appearance of likelyhood: and howbeit they were obliged by vertue of the Treaty, to have departed with their whole Army, <hi>by the first day of May, at the furthest;</hi> yet no such thing was performed, by what came to our knowledg, but to the contrary, more men were brought out of the <hi>Dutchy of Bremen,</hi> and the other <hi>Swedish Provinces,</hi> not only to burden those parts of the <hi>Kingdom of Denmark,</hi> and of the <hi>Dutchy of Holstein,</hi> where they had formerly been, but even those other parts of the said Kingdom, which during the war, had freed themselves from their oppressions by force of armes, and were exempted from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments by the <hi>Treaty of peeace.</hi> Unlesse he accounts the Swedes quitting of the Kingdom of Denmark; <hi>that intervall of time, during which they shipped their men at Kiel, and landed them at Korser, in Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land again, to invade that Island anew.</hi> Do not you therefore believe, it is very probable the King of Denmark, hath hold secret correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the Enemies of Sweden? I mean such a correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as the King of Sweden might in reason take exceptions at? for I can not immagine he pretends to debar <hi>the King of Denmark</hi> from entertaining any civill correspondency with Forraine Princes, but that presently it must be deemed a sufficient cause for a breach with the Swedes; which if so, <hi>the Pacification of Koshild would rather
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119122:7"/> savour of a tye of Servitude, than of an allyance of Friendship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the Duke of <hi>Gottorp's business,</hi> it seems the Swedes, or at least the Writer, pretends, <hi>because he the said Duke was inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Treaty of Rotshild to receive a reasonable satisfaction, that therefore the King, and Kingdom of Denmark, were to grant unto him, whatsoever they,</hi> viz. <hi>the Swedes, should think fit to demand, were it to the parting with the whole Dutchy of Holstein;</hi> and that howbeit the said Duke is now fully satisfied, the Swedes are not so, since they again rip up this business; to what end I know not, <hi>unless it vex them, that the King of Denmark hath as yet some strong places left in Holstein, since their design to surprise them took no effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the particular of the <hi>Salt,</hi> mentioned in the Book, the Swedes by Agreement were to receive for it 23000 Rixdollers, of which sum 6000 Rixdollers <hi>were by order, and in the name of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty payed, to the Swedish Ambassador Coyet, by Mr. Celio Marcellis, the remaining</hi> 17000 <hi>Rixdollers, the said Ambassador Coyet drew in several Bills of Exchange, upon Paul Klingenberg, Counsellor of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty Admiralty Court, residing in this City, to be paid to Mr. Libert Wouters: who presented them to be accepted, when the News was already arrived here, that the King of Sweden had disemharked his Army in Zealand, and was marched in an hostile manner towards Coppenhaghen,</hi> wherefore the above mentioned Klingenberg had reason to refuse the acceptation and payment of the same, <hi>and yet your Writer will needs make you believe, the Danes cannot name any sum for satisfaction of the said salt,</hi> which you see I am able to do, which am no Dane, who moreover can assure you, that the whole would have been punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>been paid, if <hi>the King of Sweden had not had a greater mind to surprise a Kingdom, than to receive</hi> 17000 <hi>Rixdollers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To demonstrate unto you with how little appearance of reason they have pretended, and also obtained <hi>the Isle of Ween,</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a long relation; and I conceive his own far-fetched reasons, and the Authors he alledges for his Witnesses, to wit, <hi>Pontanus and Whitfield,</hi> will, if rightly considered, condemn him, so will also the <hi>two Publick Ministers of France, and England,</hi> who were present when this matter was debated; and have seen the evidences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the <hi>Danish Commissioners:</hi> and the weighty reasons which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119122:7"/> they alleged, to shew how frivolous the pretences of the Swedes were: yet your Writer will prove, <hi>ex jure Gentium, that no Island can lie near to one Countrie, and yet belong to another, which lyeth at a greater distance from it;</hi> should this Argument be maintainable, <hi>then not England, but France would have a propertie in the Islands of Garne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say and Jarnesay.</hi> To what end he alledges <hi>Jus, Civile Romanorum,</hi> I know not, but do very well know, <hi>tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Roman Law is of no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, or force in the Kingdom of Denmark, much less over it;</hi> and yet I question, whether by that very Law he can make the cause of the Swedes good; for this Island was not as now first discovered, neither will they be able to prove, I believe, when it first did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and whether it was then nearer to <hi>Shonen, or to Zealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> is blamed to have held corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondency with the Hollanders; he meaneth the <hi>Lord Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> and with their <hi>Ambassador the Lord Van Buninguen;</hi> how could the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> pray you imagine, that this would disgust the Swedes? since he was not bound to take notice of any difference between them, and that State, as long as the King of Sweden did not declare them to be his Enemies, but rather himself kept a fair correspondency with them.</p>
            <p>To this the <hi>Swedes</hi> may happily object, that their intentions were only <hi>to have amused the Hollanders for a while,</hi> till they met with a fit opportunity to put their politick designs in practice against them, as they had done against <hi>Poland,,</hi> have since done against <hi>Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> and lately also against <hi>Curland.</hi> And although I must confess their said design hath since in part been manifested, yet the <hi>King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> could as then, no more foresee the same, than his own, and his Kingdoms approaching danger, which was both of greater concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, and likewise nearer at hand, ro be attempted.</p>
            <p>But put the case the <hi>Danes</hi> had as good a faculty as the Swedes do attribute unto themselves, to discern the very intimatest and most hidden intention of their Neighbours, and thereby could have discovered, that the <hi>Swedes</hi> were at so great a distance with the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> as your Writer seems to infer; yet cannot I find, <hi>that the correspondencie between his Majestie of Denmark and them, or the Letters of the Ambassador Van Buninguen</hi> (which have been annexed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119122:8"/> to the said Book) <hi>import anie thing that might cause a mis-understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, much less an open breach between the two Crowns;</hi> and to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the same Letters might have been published by the Danes or Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in their own vindication,</hi> had your Writer not saved them the labour, <hi>as well as the Danes have published the Letter of his Majestie of Denmark, writen to his publick Minister in England,</hi> but intercepted by the Swedes, <hi>and whereof they made their chief mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to prosecute the war, although they were landed in an hostile manner in the Island of Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, before the said Letter came into their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus by what I have said, and by what you will find <hi>in the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it self, you will see that his Majestie of Sweden hath had satisfaction in everie Article of the Treatie of Rotshild; save of such which it seems were of so little consequence, as his Majestie valued them not considerable enough to defer his intended invasion, onlie for a few daies, to receive the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishing thereof;</hi> although on his own part he had scarce perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med one of all the said Articles: For you know, that on the behalf of the <hi>Danes, the two whole Provinces Shonen and Bleiking, with so many strong holds, as also the Citie of Druntheim, with the adjacent Lands, and the almost invincible Fortress of Babus, in Norway, have been delivered up into the King of Swedens hands, and the Castle of Bremerfeurde, and the Forts taken hy the Norweigian Armie, have been restored unto him; the Salt and Guinea business as were agreed on, and the Duke of Gottorp had received full satisfaction;</hi> therefore I cannot imagine what your Writer can alledge to be the cause of this second new invasion, or for his mis-spending so much time, and Paper, in the rehearsal of such things as were agreed on both sides, <hi>and entirelie accomplished on the behalf of the Danes,</hi> save that he supposeth this for a sufficient cause of a breach, <hi>that perhaps the Danes parted not with it so willinglie and heartily, as the Swedes accepted of it.</hi> So that it seems the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Writer was <hi>not to give us the reasons which obliged the King of Sweden to continue the War,</hi> as in the Title he promiseth; <hi>but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, if possible, why he did not go with his victori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Armie into Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, against the Austrian Familie, whilst t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ors were at oddes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Election, and before the Emperor was ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sen;</hi> which question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less he had promised <hi>to the most Christian King, and his late Highness the Lord Protector of England;</hi> upon which account doubuless it was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119122:8"/> that <hi>he received ayds both of Men and Monies,</hi> from the one and the other; Both <hi>which Potentates</hi> it is believed, will not any longer be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to contribute those assistances, <hi>which they intended should be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed against their Enemies,</hi> towards the unjust oppression of their Friends and Allyes, and chiefly against the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in whose behalf they appeared as <hi>Mediators,</hi> and engaged themselves, as <hi>securities,</hi> for the performance of <hi>that peace,</hi> which was so solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on <hi>their engagements,</hi> concluded on, <hi>and was afterwards by the Swedes so shamefullie infringed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithstanding the Author alledgeth, <hi>that the war might have been a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an end, if the Danes had been pleased, and that his Majestie of Swedens intention was, to knit together the interest and security of both Crowns in one;</hi> which cannot possibly be made good, unless it be understood in this sence, <hi>that the King of Sweden had an intent to unite the Kingdoms o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Denmark and Norway to his own, and by making himself Master thereof, to have secured the interest of both Crowns, into hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Family;</hi> which granted, it must needs be confest, <hi>that the Danes were in the fault the war was not ended,</hi> since it seems it was not all one to them, <hi>whether they were Slaves to a King called Carolus, who could pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> right to the Crown of Denmark: or whether they were lawfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by their Crowned King Frederick, and afterwards by his Son, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>istian, their Elected Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus far, with an intention to have marked some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> and <hi>falshoods</hi> contain'd in the Paper, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you, I was diverted by a visit of <hi>Mr. N. an English Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>wly arived from <hi>England,</hi> where I had the happiness to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>nted with him, during my aboad there, whose presence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> acceptable unto me, as well by reason of the Friendship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> contracted with him, as that I so opportunely met with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by him to hear some News from your parts.</p>
            <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> scarce had he satisfied my curiosity, when as perceiving a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my ear, he would have taken his leave, apprehending least <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might divert me from my accustomed employments, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to assure him, that I was not any otherwise engaged, save <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the acquitting of my self of that duty, whereunto all persons of Honor were bound, <hi>To defend the truth, and to disabuse their friends,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119122:9"/> and briefly that I was a writing a Letter unto your self, to let you see, <hi>that a Pamphlet lately printed at London, entituled, A True Relation, &amp;c. whereby the Author pretended to justifie the Swedish unwarrantable proceedings, contained nothing less than the truth:</hi> Alack! said my Friend, what an unnecessary a task have you taken upon your self? for it is impossible, but that the party to whom you do write, living at <hi>London,</hi> must needs know, that the <hi>Relation you mention</hi> is no more regarded or accounted of there, than those <hi>Astrological Predictions,</hi> which are printed in the same place, especially since the world hath taken notice, that <hi>the Swedes, in imitation of Saul,</hi> have addrest themselves to <hi>Southsayers and wizzards.</hi> The chief whereof they have gained by a chain of Gold, which hath so inveigled the rest of that <hi>Tribe,</hi> as that promising themselves the like recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations, they have proceeded to vomit out <hi>Slanders</hi> and <hi>Invectives</hi> against those <hi>Princes and States,</hi> which are allyed unto <hi>his Highness the Lord Protector,</hi> in as horrid a manner as the former; and the reason why all of them have not followed his footsteps, doubtless is, that in the first place they should see, how his aspersions would rellish, and be disgested, and whether his Highness the Lord Protector being duly informed thereof, would not cause him to <hi>contemplate the Celestial constellations, through a Hempen casement:</hi> since none of those <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which he so horridly calumniates, to wit, <hi>His Majesty the King of Denmark,</hi> His <hi>Electoral Highness the Duke of Brandenbourgh,</hi> and the <hi>Lord States of the United Provinces,</hi> would refuse that satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction unto his Highness, should any of their Subjects have so far forgotten themselves, as to have vented such abominations against any of his Ministers, much less against his Highness own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</p>
            <p>And expecting my Friend would have added something, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Penners of your <hi>Mercurius, and Publique Intelligencers,</hi> which he did not; I at length asked him what opinion was harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in those parts concerning them? telling him that as often as they were communicated unto us, we met with a great deal of pastime therein, specyfying unto him, amongst other things, a pretty pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, which my self had met with, in one of them, concerning the behaviours, which your Intellegencer Fathers upon two of the King
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119122:9"/> of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Senators, the Lord <hi>Magnus Hogh,</hi> and <hi>Christian Skeel,</hi> who being sent to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> when he appeared with his Army before Coppenhaggen, to know the reason of this so suddain and unexpected invasion, should, as your Intelligencer pretends, have been so throughly convinced by the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of the unjustness of their Kings cause, as that they resolved not any longer to serve their said Master in those his unlawfull under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. Whereby your said Intelligencer, would needs make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was better acquainted with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the Court of <hi>Denmark,</hi> than the Senators and Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the said Kingdom themselves, amongst which, those two Honorable Persons take place, and whom he endeavoured to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to the derision of the whole <hi>English</hi> Nation, by forestalling that they should have wept like Children on the aforesaid oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion.</p>
            <p>Whereunto my Friend replyed; that he had observed, it was a piece of pollicy practised by the Swedes, to gain all the <hi>Newes Mongers,</hi> throughout the whole World, by what means, he knew not; and that if I did but reflect on what is printed in <hi>Germanie</hi> in <hi>France, and in Holland,</hi> I should finde they did generally all of them favour the <hi>Swedish Partie,</hi> as well as at London; so that the one could not well be blamed, without the accusing of all the rest: I, but said I, the English is more passionately inclined to them, then all the others; That's not for want of will in the others, said he, but they have not the same advantage, being not at so great a distance from those places whence they publish the said News. Besides, that we being <hi>penitus toto divisi orbe Britanni,</hi> do satisfie our selves with an indifferent and superficial knowledge of foreign affairs, without questioning the particulars of them so much as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations do, whose Writers would not attain to their ends; which is to preserve their credit, to be serviceable to the Swedish interests, and to comply with their own, in the vending of their Pamphlets. However there be those amongst us, who very well know, that all is not Gospel that is pinned upon us; and I can also assure you, That several considerable Personages, reflecting on that very passage, which you have even now related, told me, both his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119122:10"/> Highness and the Counsel would er'e-long have such like abuse, prevented. Why then said I, pray tell me, what is the matters since as you say, you credit not the News-books, nor the Astrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Predictions, neither that very Pamphlet, that you harbour so good an opinion of the Swedes? who have no sollider grounds to justifie, their proceedings by. Who told you said he, that we have so good an opinion of them? all the World, said I, and especially the Swedes themselves, who very confidently affirm, that <hi>England</hi> will assist them, in and against all parties whatsoever; soft and fair said he, it is doubtfull, whether <hi>England</hi> will so far engage with the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as it seems you apprehend. But this I dare say, that <hi>England</hi> will do much for the Protestant cause, whereof the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> is the Promoter: At which Allegation of the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> being the Promoter of the Protestant Cause, I could no longer contain, but freely asked my Friend, Whether he thought the Protestant Religion ever had had a greater Enemy than the King of <hi>Sweden?</hi> since the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor the Papishes in the valleys of <hi>Piedmond</hi> had not spilt so much innocent Protestant blood in all their Massacres, as the said King had done; who dis-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled and weakned all Protestant Princes, in such an unheard of manner, as that those of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may totally extirpate them whensoever they please, which doubtless they will not omit to do, as soon as they shall meet with an opportunity to effect the same, especially when as they shall understand, we are so far from condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, as that we hold it for a Protestant Maxime, That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of advancing our Religion, we may usurp our Neighbours possessions; as if God had given us but nine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, whereas they have ten.</p>
            <p>Rest your self satisfied answered my Friend, what I have alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is but by way of discourse, and to give you part of what I have often heard by such, as were great <hi>Sticklers</hi> and <hi>Abettors</hi> of the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish party, for I would not have you to believe, that we are such <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks,</hi> as to suffer our selves to be perswaded, <hi>That the ruining and destroying of the Kingdome of Denmark, Porussia, Curland, and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of the Prince Elector of Brandenbourg, the enslaving of the City of Bremen (the sole amongst all the Hans, and free Imperial
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119122:10"/> Townes, which as we, does professe the true Reformed Religion) can or may advance the Protestant Cause.</hi> And to tell you the truth, we are not a little displeased, that the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> did not rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his victorious Forces against some other Parts, <hi>then against Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> But since he is engaged in that undertaking, and that he hath so many enemies to bukcle with, and amongst the rest the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Forces,</hi> we conceive, we cannot well abandon him, without the giving of an opportunity unto the <hi>Emperor,</hi> to send a considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble relief unto the <hi>King of Spain,</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> to overwhelm our Conquests there; <hi>which by the Swedes at London, is assured to be the present Emperors design, as soon as the Swedish Army shall have received the least foil, and that the rest of the Allyes shall be in a condition to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose their proceedings, with their own Forces, without the standing in need of the Emperors Ayde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon I demanded of my Friend whether or no that were his Highnesse the <hi>Lord Protectors,</hi> and the <hi>Councells</hi> opinion? How would you have me to know that, said he, who am but a private Person, and bear no Publick Charge, or Office, in my Country? and where the Affaires of State are carried on with so admirable a conduct and secrecy, as that we cannot affirm any thing, till we see it effected; what I have told you is but my bare opinion, and the sence of those who dive no deeper into the Publick State of Affaires then my self. I really believe you, said I, <hi>For in case your opinion twere admitted of in your Country; you needed but to give the Kingdomes of Denmark, and Norway, to the King of Sweden; (who being more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Master of all the Baltick Sea, two or three places only excepted;) and therby the State of Great Brittane would be exposed unto the same dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, wherein it was formerly, when those three Kingdomes were under the Dominion of one sole Potentate; who notwithstanding had not the Sea-Ports of the Baltick Sea, which are, worth at least another Kingdome;</hi> And all this by the meer apprehension which it pleaseth the <hi>Swedes</hi> to infuse into you; <hi>that the Emperor will afford the King of Spain Forces and Relief;</hi> whereby you might be said, to immitate the Skit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish horse, whieh being frightned, and startting at a shaddow, leaps out of the path, and puts out one of his eyes.</p>
            <p>Or in case you will not grant it to be a meer shaddow, which you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119122:11"/> are startled at, but a reallity, <hi>that the Emperor both may, and will give assistance and aides to the Spaniards:</hi> you must at least confesse, that this can only pass for a small scratch, to which you will needs apply a plaister, <hi>whiles you neglect and omit the curing af a dangerous wound, which may prove a mortal one, and destructive to the whole body,</hi> This you will infallibly do, unlesse you resolve <hi>to be assisting and aiding to the King of Denmark, thereby to render him capable to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the power of one, who otherwayes will not stick to pester you ere long, (as he a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> present does trouble the rest of his Neighbours;) if not timely prevented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherunto my friend replyed, that he found my Reasons and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations were well grounded, assuring me that <hi>the raynes of the State, where you are, were at present in the hands of so sagacious a Prince, as would not be induced to neglect the providing for the good, tranquillity and security of those Estates, wherewithal the All-mighty hath intrusted him. To contribute to the ambitious designs of one, who hath so ill rewarded those, who have been instrumental in the enlarging of the Crown which he now weares; for no other reason, save that he conceives it not vast e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to his minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover that His Highnesse was minded to call a Parliament, which being the grand Representative of the Nation, and his Great Councel, would doubtlesse close in and cooperate with His Highnesse, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of most just, equitable, and Generous resolutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus ended our discourse; wherewithal I shall also finish this my already overlong Epistle; <hi>Beseeching the All-mighty to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose all Christian Princes, unto Peace, and tranquillity; which we might soon promise our selves in these Parts, in case the King of Sweden, would content himself, and rest satisfied with that; which by reason of a long possession, he may in some manner call his own; as well is his Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours do, with that which undoubtedly, and without any question, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Hamborough <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 15<seg rend="sup">th.</seg>
                     <hi>of December,</hi> 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119122:11"/>
            <head>AN EXACT RELATION OF THE Transactions &amp; Proceedings Between the KINGS of DENMARK and SWEDEN, AND Between their MINISTERS, From the Treaty of Pacification at <hi>Roschilt,</hi> on the 26. <hi>Febr.</hi> 1657./1658. till the Breach of the said Peace by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> on the 9. of <hi>August</hi> of this present Year.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is manifest to all the World, how and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Rivers,</hi> wherein the greatest strength of the <hi>Danish</hi> Islands consists, were, by an unheard of Cold, and most f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erce Frost, so closed up and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with Ice, as that, since the memory of man, it was never known to be so before: whereupon, in the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> last past of this present year, 1658. the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> met with a wished opportunity to march over the Ice with his whole Army and Canon, and to fall upon the Island of <hi>Funen,</hi> thence into <hi>Laland, Falster,</hi> and finally into <hi>Zealand;</hi> whereby he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119122:12"/> constrained the King of <hi>Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> through the earnest and labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mediation of the <hi>King of France</hi> his <hi>Ambassador,</hi> and by the interposition of <hi>the Lord Protector of Englands Extraordinary Envoy,</hi> together with such <hi>Commissioners as were deputed from Copenhaghen</hi> and <hi>the King of Swedens Plenipotentiaries,</hi> to yield unto an irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and most advantagious Peace, both for <hi>the King and Crown of Sweden:</hi> The first Treaty thereon being held at <hi>Wordinghburg</hi> and <hi>Tostrup,</hi> and the Conclusion of the whole being perfected at <hi>Rots<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilt</hi> on the 26 day of <hi>February</hi> last past: whereupon immediately the aforesaid <hi>King of Denmark,</hi> together with <hi>the Senators of the Kingdom,</hi> did approve of, and confirm the same in due form; and in like manner <hi>the King of Sweden</hi> and <hi>his Senators</hi> did ratifie it: In reference whereunto the Articles of Agreement were solemnly delivered up and enterchanged at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> by the mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of both parties.</p>
            <p>And although <hi>the King of Denmark,</hi> in conformity to the said Treaty, did yield up, resign, and quit to <hi>the King of Sweden,</hi> such and so many stately Towns, Fortresses and Sea-Ports, as the <hi>Swedes</hi> with all their Forces of Arms could not have hoped to have sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued in many years together; as namely the noble Provinces of <hi>Schonen</hi> and <hi>Blecking,</hi> with <hi>Halland</hi> to boot: (which was onely by way of engagement formerly made over to <hi>the Crown of Sweden</hi> for a certain term of years welnigh expired;) besides the Fortresses of <hi>Malmoh, Lands-Crone, Christianopel, Elsingburg, Christianstad</hi> in <hi>Shonen</hi> and <hi>Blekingen;</hi> as also <hi>Laholm, Halmstadt</hi> and <hi>Warburgh</hi> in <hi>Halland;</hi> besides the two most famous and Kingly Territories in <hi>Norway,</hi> to wit, the almost invincible Fortress and Domain of <hi>Bahues,</hi> and the Royalty and City of <hi>Druntheim,</hi> with all the places thereunto belonging, together with the Isle of <hi>Bornholm;</hi> having also restored all <hi>Yempterland,</hi> and finally the Castle of <hi>Bremer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veurde;</hi> both which places, had formerly during the Wars, been taken by the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Forces: all which was thus effected in conformity unto the Articles of Peace; an Extract whereof is here annexed out of the 16 <hi>Article,</hi> marked with the letter <hi>A.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> After <hi>the King of Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> I say, had delivered up the 2000 Horse, and had complyed with all whereunto he was bound by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119122:12"/> the said Treaty, assuring himself, that the <hi>Swedes</hi> on their part would give order for the withdrawing of their Soldiers out of those <hi>Danish</hi> Provinces, Dukedoms, and Countries as were posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> specified in the said Article, and that they would clear the said Provinces on the appointed <hi>first day of May,</hi> of this present year, without any further contest or dispute, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the said Agreement: Yet to the contrary the same was from time to time delayed by frivolous pretentions, and in the mean while the Countries where the <hi>Swedes</hi> lay were exhausted and totally ruined: The <hi>Swedes</hi> not at all regarding those Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which were made concerning their quartering in the said respective Countries, according to their own good liking, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference whereunto those Regiments, which were quartered in the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> were to be maintained there in a civil way till the first of <hi>May;</hi> but they would not therewith be satisfied, exacting such high Treatments as they themselves pleased; and moreover pressed and forced in more Regiments to quarter in <hi>Denmark,</hi> in <hi>Jutland,</hi> in <hi>Funen,</hi> and in <hi>Holstein,</hi> then was agreed on; the whole contrary to the express meaning and Contents of the 17 <hi>Article</hi> of the said Treaty of Peace annexed, and marked with the letter <hi>B.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas, after the Ratification of the concluded Peace, any other Treaties between the Deputies and Commissioners of both parties, were desired to be held here at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> for the begetting and setling of a better understanding; The <hi>King of Denmark</hi> did not onely willingly admit of the <hi>King of Swedens Ambassadors,</hi> the Lord <hi>Steno Bielk</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Julius Coyet,</hi> but also appointed <hi>Commissioners</hi> of his own to confer and agree with them. And immediately the <hi>Swedish</hi> Ambassadors, at their very first arrival in the month of <hi>March,</hi> having made overtures of a <hi>neerer Union</hi> and <hi>stricter Aliance</hi> betwixt these <hi>two Northern Crowns,</hi> several conferences were thereon held, at which after the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Articles of the pretended Union had been discussed and pondered, and were for the most part assented unto by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and though on the behalf of <hi>Denmark</hi> the said Aliance was held to be as good as setled and concluded; yet nevertheless there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119122:13"/> was no notice in the world to be taken, how that the <hi>Swedish</hi> Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors did without any just reason and cause break off the said Treaty, on this bare allegation, <q rend="inline">That since <hi>the Crown of Denmark</hi> (amongst other things) did reserve it self in the not intermeddling in those Wars wherein <hi>the Crown of Sweden</hi> was as then involved, the said Union would therefore prove to be but as a <hi>publique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test,</hi> whereby the Enemies of the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> might disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that the <hi>Danes</hi> were unwilling to espouse the <hi>Swedish</hi> cause, and that therefore it would be better to remit and suspend the said Union till a more convenient opportunity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But by this time the <hi>Swedish</hi> Proceedings do evidently manifest, That it was not the pretended Aliance or Union with <hi>Denmark</hi> they so much cared for, as onely to gain time, whereby to enlarge their Conquest, and to breed a difference between, and to separate the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> from her Alies.</p>
            <p>This Treaty of Union being thus ceased, the <hi>Swedish</hi> Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors did most eagerly press the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners to have a new additional Declaration drawn up concerning the Pacification which was made at <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>schilt:</hi> And in the mean while the <hi>Gottorpish</hi> Ambassadors arriving at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> and desiring the performance of that satisfaction which the Duke of <hi>Holstein</hi> was to receive <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reason,</hi> in reference unto the 22 <hi>Article</hi> of the Treaty of Peace annexed, and marked with the letter <hi>C.</hi> The <hi>Swedish Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors</hi> immediately took <hi>the Holstein. Ambassadors</hi> part, spoke very high, and pretended strange things; notwithstanding the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> condescended so far to their desires, as that he yielded the Soveraignty over the <hi>Dukedom of Sleswig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the Island of Femcren, the best part of the Deanry and Chapter of Sleswigh, and the whole Lordship of Swa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stead;</hi> (although himself and his renowned Predecessors had enjoyed a quiet Possession and Government of the said place by a just and lawful well-grounded Title for the space of 72 years, and) made it over to <hi>Duke Frederich of Sleswigh, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein and Gottorp,</hi> to preserve and increase a brotherly understanding betwixt them; whereby the <hi>Gottorpish</hi> Ambassadors Demands were so far satisfied, as that <hi>the Swedish Ambassadors, and the Duke of Holsteins Ambassadors,</hi> especially their respective Superiors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119122:13"/> to be satisfied therewith; as the several Instruments and Deeds, drawn up, setled and confirmed on that Particular, and more especially the Letters of Thanks, and Acknowledgments, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from the Duke of <hi>Holstein</hi> upon that account, do sufficiently manifest and prove.</p>
            <p>So likewise did the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> on his part make the the more hast to conclude the <hi>Gottorpish</hi> affaires, in regard that the <hi>Swedish Ministers,</hi> as also the the <hi>French Ambassador, and</hi> the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Extraordinary Envoye,</hi> did give severall assurances, that so soon as this agreement should be concluded on, the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Forces should immediatly withdraw out of the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Territories; whereupon likewise the <hi>Swedish Ambassador</hi> did dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch a Letter to <hi>the Lord high Admiral Wrangle,</hi> General of the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Army; much to this portent. <hi>That in regard thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Treaties will be speedily ended, and are already upon their conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, they thought good to give notice thereof to his Excellency: that accordingly, (though by his Majesty of Swedens Orders;) he might govern himself in the withdrawing of the Forces, and might prepare himself to march away with them.</hi> This Letter was sent under a fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seal to his <hi>Majesty of Denmark,</hi> by way of notification, who sent it by an Expresse to General <hi>Wrangle,</hi> though no such thing ensu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d thereon.</p>
            <p>Nor could it enter into the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> thoughts, (nor any ones else) that after the conclusion and ratification of the pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>at Rotschilt</hi> any other declarations or specifications were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite, the same being so clear and manifestly expressed, as that there needed not an ampler Explanation, or Elucidation, or inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereon, which was also quite and clean contrary to the intent and purport of the said Pacification of <hi>Roschilt:</hi> since in the XI. Article of the said Treaty annexed, and marked with the letter D. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> there is an especiall proviso made, that all those particulars, which were not altered by the said Treaty, should be regulated according to the tenor of the former agreements made at <hi>Stetin, Soero de &amp; Bremsebrohe</hi> betwixt the two aforesaid renowned Crowns.</p>
            <p>And to the end, there might yet a better understanding be set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that all difficulties might be removed, as also that the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119122:14"/>
               <hi>Danish</hi> Kingdomes, Dukedomes and Provinces might be the soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner eased and disburdened from, and of the heavy <hi>Swedish</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings, Contributions, and the other unsufferable Warlike expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and oppressiones which were forced upon them, expressely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the contents of the XVII. Article, of the Treaty of Peace annexed, and marked with the letter B. The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> was pleased to yeeld to the same, and granted unto the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> several things, which he might with a great deal of Equity and Justice have refused.</p>
            <p>Moreover the urged <hi>Explanation</hi> was first projected by the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish</hi> Ambassadors, and was by them delivered up and insinuated to the <hi>Danish</hi> Commissioners, who as at first, did amongst others, find such a clause therein, as was by the <hi>Swedes</hi> explained thus, in the third Article of the <hi>Roschilt's Pacification,</hi> annexed and marked with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="E"/> the letter E. That the word <hi>hostile</hi> contained in the said Article, (and which, on the behalf of <hi>Denmark</hi> was otherwise inserted on purpose) <q rend="inline">should have no other signification save that the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> is thereby authorized to do and omit in the Eastern Sea, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever she pleaseth, and seemeth good unto her; whereby the <hi>Swedes</hi> themselves did immediately give occasion of a necessary shrewd suspition, of a strange contradiction, and of the delayes which thereby ensued.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Since which, the vast designes of the afore said Crown of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> did not only evidently appeare, but also were more manifest, whenas the King of <hi>Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks</hi> Commissioners requiring that in the additionall Declaration, it should be specified; that both the aforesaid Crownes should particulary endeavor, that the Traffick and commerce in the Eastern Sea should remain free and secure without any interruption or molestation, and not to permit or suffer any action to be perpetrated therein, which might tend to the prejudice of the Royalties, Priviledges and Freedomes of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parties: The aforesaid <hi>Swedish</hi> Ambassadors did plainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse the same, and brought the businesse so about, as that the said Article was wholly agreed upon, in the favor and to the advantage of the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although several Articles which were run over again in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119122:14"/> said additional Declaration, especially concerning the Duties of the Sea-Passes and Certificates in the <hi>Sound</hi> were agreed upon, <hi>by the Ambassadors and Commissioners on both sides, at a Conference held by them.</hi> and that even in the said Swedish Project or Draught it was specified and set down in the Margin, for the better manifesting of the same, that the said Articles were so setled. Yet however in another Conference the Swedish Ambassadors did dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve and alter the said Articles, whereby the Treaty was the more delayed: and when these things were represented to them, they gave no other Answer, save, that they had received other Orders thereon from their King and Master.</p>
            <p>In the like manner the said Swedish Ambassadors did in their said additional Declaration insert, that whereas in the Treaty of Pacification the <hi>Lordship of Druntheim</hi> was resigned and yielded to the <hi>Crown of Sweden,</hi> so in like manner it was to be understood, that the <hi>Bishops Sea Druntheim</hi> was also thereby resigned and yielded up, which nevertheless doth oppugn and contradict the true meaning and right Sence of the sixt Article of the Instrument of Peace, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed and marked with the Letter F. in which there is not so much <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> as a word to be found, intimating the yielding up of the <hi>Bishops Sea of Druntheim:</hi> but on the part of the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> it was more then sufficiently demonstrated, that <hi>the Bishops Sea of Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theim</hi> had no dependancy on the Lordship, being separated from the same. Hower the Swedish final resolution thereon, (as before) was, that their King had commanded them to persist therein.</p>
            <p>And they failed so little: by their pretending to include this Territory within the said Dominion: of the inlarging of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to a greater extent, then they formerly were known to be, as that they named those Territories, which are situated in the <hi>Drunthimer Bishops Sea, the Nordlanden,</hi> and would comprize them therein as an Appurtenance belonging to the same. Which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand one of the Sweedish Ambassadors, namely <hi>Cojet,</hi> pressed so far, as that when it was told him, there was no such thing contained in the Article of Peace, he made answer unto the Danish Commissioners, that it should cost the Earl <hi>Ulefelt</hi> and the Senator <hi>Steno Bielche</hi> their Heads, that they had not herein
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119122:15"/> followed their Instructions, and that at the beginning of the Treaty they had not urged the Points of the <hi>Norlands,</hi> and taken care, that it might be comprehended in the said Article. But when as they perceived, they could not compasse their Designe herein, they endeavored separately to bring the said <hi>Norlanden</hi> either by way of exchange, or for moneys under the Crown of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Insomuch that during the said <hi>Negotiations</hi> there was nothing more common to the Swedes then this, to wit, when they had made an unreasonable and harsh demand: which the Danes were forced to grant, to avoid the greater evil of the two: they then would advance and propose another demand as unreasonable as the former, if not far worse: And then for their last argument and reason of such their unjust demands; in which they would not be contradicted or gainsayed: they declared, <hi>That the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresse of Frederichs Odde should not be delivered up, nor the Swedish Army be drawen out of the King of Denmarks, Territories, until such time as they had consented to all their demands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewise it is known to all men what passed in the said Treaty concerning the Isle of <hi>Ween:</hi> for the <hi>Gotterpish</hi> or <hi>Holstein</hi> Treaty was no sooner concluded and signed, but the Swedes did immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately frame a pretence to the said Island, that so on that account they might continue the enquartering of their Forces in the Danish Territories in the same manner as before. Whereas to gain yet more time for themselves, and to keep their Forces there, they did without any ground at all surmise, that the said Island belonged to <hi>Shonen,</hi> although it hath no dependancy at all on <hi>Shonen,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the description of all both <hi>Modern and Ancient Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers and Geographers,</hi> but from time out of minde, hath and doth resort under the Isle of <hi>Zealand,</hi> as well concerning the Civil as Ecclesiastical jurisdiction; the subjects and Inhabitants of <hi>Ween</hi> paying in their Contributions and Assessements unto the Bayliff residing then at <hi>Chronenbourgh</hi> in <hi>Zealand;</hi> besides which the said Island used the same Laws of <hi>Zealand:</hi> and King <hi>Christian</hi> the Fourth, on the 24. day of <hi>May,</hi> 1634. at the instance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of the said Inhabitants did grant (only during his pleasure) that they might make their appearances, and be judged at the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119122:15"/>
               <hi>Judicature sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Shonen,</hi> which was but three leagues distant from them, and not by the <hi>judicature seat of Zealand,</hi> which was at eleven leagues distance; But with this reservation however, dated <hi>January</hi> the 26. <hi>Anno</hi> 1647. <hi>That the Inhabitants of Shonen being a free people, the Subjects of Ween should continue as Vassals, or Gleb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e adscriptitii of Zealand, and not be judged by the Laws of Shonen, but by the Laws of Zealand.</hi> Notwithstanding <hi>the King of Denmark,</hi> for quietnesse sake, and to free his Territories and Subjects from the intollerable oppressions, and heavy burthen of the Swedish forces, promised rather to remit the said Island to the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor were the Swedes herewith satisfied neither, but anew, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended satisfaction for the <hi>three Ships loden with Salt,</hi> which formerly in time of war were detained <hi>in the Sound,</hi> which said ships they set at so high an estimate, as that the value of the Salt, and other pretended Merchandises in the said ships, were overrated above the one half; notwithstanding it was fully concluded, <hi>That the said Salt ships with all their equipage should be restored, and in lieu of the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a considera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mme of money was payed.</hi> And whereas it now seemed that all things were duly repaired and cleered, and that the Swedes could not possibly have found out any further pretensions: They to gain more time, did exhibit another pretended grievance, whereon they demanded satisfaction; to wit, for the booty which the King of Denmarks subjects (during the time of open and declared wars) had taken from the Swedish Company of <hi>Guinea,</hi> for the which at first they demanded 200000, afterwards 300000, and finally 400000 Rixdollars, whereas it is sufficiently well known, that the said losses did not amount unto so much by far, and at most could not exceed the summe of 100000 Rixdollars. And although the King of Denmark was only obliged <hi>to restore the bare Castels and Fortresses in Guinea, without any Caenon, ammunitions or provisions,</hi> according the contents of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e 14 Article of the Treaty of Peace, annexed and marked with the Letter G, which was sufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="G"/> and shewen to the Ambassadors, yet however <hi>the King of Denmark</hi> to hasten the long desired and promised departure of the Swedish Forces out of his Dominions, did so far condescend unto this their most unreasonable demand, as that he promised to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119122:16"/> make good the 400000 Rixdollars, for reparation and satisfaction of the losses the Sweeds pretended thereby to have suffered. To the payment of which summe the Swedes first demanded some Land should be engaged and pawned, and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that several <hi>Merchants of Hamborough</hi> should engage to pay the said summe within one years time, as their own debt.</p>
            <p>Whereupon <hi>the King of Denmark</hi> represented to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> that this their last demand was impossible to be performed, by reason that <hi>the Crown of Denmark</hi> in that conjuncture of time, (as long as the Swedish Forces were not withdrawn out of his Territories) had not so much credit; And although his Majestie of Denmark would have engaged himself to have seen the same performed, thereby to have freed His Dominions from the intollerable burden of the Military extorsions, yet there would no ear at all be given thereunto. However, to the end it might not be said, that the King of Denmark had omitted any thing (though never so difficult, were it in his power to performe the same) which might tend to the good of his Dominions, and of his Subjects, did finally proffer unto the Swedish Ambassadors, his own and his Senators Bond for the payment of the said 400000 Rixdollers, besides some consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Territories, whereof they were to enjoy the Revenues, in case the said payment should not be made in due time, and un till such time, as the <hi>Castels in Guineae</hi> should be restored, hoping that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> would have therewith remained satisfied, and would have given order for the withdrawing of his forces out of the King of Denmarks Dominions, according unto the agreement of the Treaty of Peace, and the which was so often with infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble engagements promised.</p>
            <p>But there was nothing at all concluded nor performed hereon, save only that one of the Swedish <hi>Plenipotentiary Ambassadors, Peter Julius Cojet</hi> (who till that time had remained here) departed with the said resolutions from hence to Holstein, with an intent to make a verbal relation of all the said Proceedings to the King his Master, promising that he would both contribute to facilitate the desired marching away of the Swedish Forces, and that within a fortnight he would return again; comporting himself in such a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119122:16"/> serious and seigned way, and giving such good words and fair promises, as that amongst the honest and well meaning people, it was beleeved, that all his proceedings were real, and that in a very short space of time he would have compassed the freeing of the Kingdoms and Dominions belonging to his Majestie of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, from the heavy oppressions they did lye under, and that he would have forthwith returned with good tydings thereof: but the event did shortly after evidence the contrary.</p>
            <p>Now when as in this wise entire, full, and more then compleat satisfaction had been given to the King of Sweden, even to his most unjust and unreasonable demands, that all the Countreyes and strong places (agreed on in the Articles of the treaty of Peace) were delivered up, the <hi>Castle of Bremerveurde</hi> restored, and that the evacuation and reciprocal surrendring of the <hi>Island</hi> of <hi>Funen,</hi> and the strong place of <hi>Fredericks Odde</hi> was expected, and the which ought to have been yielded up by the Swedes, at the same time as <hi>Bremerford</hi> was by the <hi>King of Denmark,</hi> the rather in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thar the aforesaid <hi>Swedish Ambassadors</hi> had showen unto the <hi>Senators of the King of Denmark,</hi> an Original Letter from the King of Sweden containing this particular among others. <hi>As soon as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merford shall be restored to us, the Island of Funen shall also be evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and cleared.</hi> But it seems the Sweeds were otherwise minded, and resolved, as the event sufficiently manifests.</p>
            <p>When as, a great complaint was made and forestalled by the Swedes, as if the two thousand horse and men which had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised unto them were not effectually delivered, pretending that by reason hereof they were constrained to defer their marching away; whereas it is sufficiently manifest, how and in what manner <hi>the King of Denmark,</hi> did two dayes before the <hi>Agreement at Rosehilt,</hi> which was concluded on the 26. of <hi>February</hi>) to wit on the 24. of the said moneth cause the said 20000 horse (consisting in three several Regiments and their respective Companies, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Major General Joachim Traempen, Collonel Bertram Ranzow,</hi> and the <hi>Captain of horse Drachen Felsen</hi>) to be delivered over unto the Swedes hard by <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> at the place called the <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kroogh,</hi> by the said <hi>Major General Trampen,</hi> insomuch as in this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119122:17"/> particular there was no delay at all; but afterwards when as seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the said Troopers being in the King of Swedens service (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their resignment in the aforesaid manner) contrary to the King of Denmarks knowledge and will, did in a clandestine way hide and absent themselves, and were run away from their colours; inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that shortly alter, in the moneth of <hi>March,</hi> at the Solemn and friendly meeting of both the said Kings at <hi>Fredericksborgh,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other particulars, the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> alledging to the <hi>King of Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> that several of the said Troopers were run away, the King of Sweden himself, did in the presence of the <hi>L. Ernest Albreht of Eberste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> (the King of Denmarks field Marshal) declare, that if so be the Muster rowls of the said men might be delivered unto him, he would cause those Troopers which were missing to be sought for, and to be brought back to their Colours again, since the greatest part of them were inhabitants of <hi>Shonen,</hi> (now a Province of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;) this was very willingly and speedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y consented unto by the King of Denmark, and immediately afterwards the said Muster rowls were delivered to the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> by the <hi>Danish Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor at Gottenb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urgh, the Lord Offujuel,</hi> after which the runaway Troopers not only were speedily by the Swedes themselves sought up in the <hi>Province of Shonen,</hi> but were for the most part (if not all of them) found again, and brought to their Colours.</p>
            <p>But this was not at all regarded, nor was there any heed taken of those things which were bespoken and assented unto at <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricksborgh;</hi> and the King of Sweden anew, caused instances to be made for the delivery of a thousand Troopers more, the which having been over and above assented unto, and was profered, the said Troopers being presented to the Swedish Officers in <hi>Jutland</hi> and <hi>Holstein,</hi> which were appointed to receive them, as namely <hi>Major General Botticher,</hi> did move several difficulties, which were not contained in the Treaty of Peace, at length deferred the time for their admittance, and shortly after bespoke that there should be no Danes among them, excepted against the Troopers, for having no Cloaks, that their Saddles and Pistols pleased them not, that their horses were not all of one s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ze, that they would not admit of their Corporals and under Officers, servants in the Muster rowls;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119122:17"/> that above the said numbers, there were to be 60 or 65 Troopers more, and several such like objections, as it is apparent by the <hi>Field Marshal Ebersteins</hi> letter to the aforesaid <hi>Major General Botti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> annexed and marked with the Letter H, whereby both the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> Officers and Soldiers grew the more impatient, so that the Danes were forced to yield to their harsh demands, and to return the Troopers again into their old quarters, where they had formerly layen, after they had been in this manner thus proffered by the <hi>Field Marshall Eberstein,</hi> to the <hi>Major General Botticher,</hi> till such time as it pleased the Swedes to receive them, which they purpose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deferred, the better to bring their subtle designe now at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, with the lesser contradiction to a conclusion; when as 500 Troop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had formerly been delivered them in <hi>Jutland</hi> and the rest in <hi>Holstein</hi> not far from <hi>Gluckstadt,</hi> whereby the King of Denmark thought himself secured, and in such a peaceable condition, as that the <hi>Kingdom of Denmark</hi> was void of all warlike preparations, and so little thought upon new levies, as that they disbanded those Forces which were on foot; insomuch as that the <hi>Ambassador of Sweden</hi> did request and assure his <hi>Majestie of Denmark,</hi> not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the making of any new unnecessary levies. And whilst we were in a dayly expectation of the so much desired, and looked for, nay promised marching of and drawing of the Swedish Forces, we received the sad news, that the Marsh lands and Territoris pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for the maintaining of the guarrisons of <hi>Gluckstadt, Crempe, Kenscourgh</hi> and <hi>Pinenberg</hi> were burdened and oppressed with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable taxations and inquartering of Soldiers, flat and plain against the direct and absolute promises made by the <hi>King of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> to the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> at their personal meeting at <hi>Fredericks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh</hi> in the Moneth of March, when as he assured the <hi>King of Denmark,</hi> that those Marsh lands should be freed from all inquarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings whatsoever, as also contrary to the <hi>King of Swedens.</hi> Orders in writing when he was last at <hi>Gottenbourgh,</hi> which he gave to the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> of <hi>Sultsbach</hi> the General of the Horse, concerning the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar cleering of the Territory of <hi>Rensbourgh,</hi> as it appeared under the Letter I annexed, and which said Order was delivered to the <hi>King of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Denmarks</hi> Ambassador at <hi>Gottenbourgh</hi> under flying Seal, to the end
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119122:18"/> his Majestie of Denmark might rest satisfied, that it should be the better observed.</p>
            <p>By which proceedings the <hi>King of Denmarks guarrisons</hi> were not only defrauded of their useful subsistencies, but also the <hi>Inhabitants of those parts,</hi> by the said intollerable, oppression<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, were utterly ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and undone.</p>
            <p>So likewise in the same <hi>moneth of March,</hi> the Palsegrave, did fall into south D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tmarsh with 2000 horse, and there exacted moneys and severall other taxations by violence, as also forced considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble summes of money to be levied in the Territories of <hi>Rensbrough,</hi> where a Swedish Colonel did require only for the dayly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his own person 313 Rix dollers, and besides himself there were severall other officers, who pretended the same allowance, and the like enquartrings were not only imposed on the <hi>Inhabitants of the Dukedomes of Holstein,</hi> but the <hi>Dutchy of Sleswigh</hi> was also for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to contribute towards the setting forth of the <hi>King of the Swedens Fleet,</hi> and by that means, was little or not at all the better for the foregoing Pacification.</p>
            <p>Over and above which notwithstanding the security allowed for the free Passage of letters, and of those safe conducts, which were granted by the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> himself, the Swedes at <hi>Flensbourgh</hi> did detain the Posts sent by the <hi>King of Denmarks Senators</hi> into <hi>Holstein,</hi> and by others to the said King, opened their dispatches, red the same, and never sent them forwards, according to their directions, but published some of them in print, contrary to the <hi>King of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> promise, and engagment under his hand and seale.</p>
            <p>And although the poor inhabitants did with severall summs of money often times redeem the aforesaid taxations, and thereby gave content to their trooopes, presently afterwards other <hi>Swedish forces</hi> violently entred the said parts again, and renewed the said taxations and exactions in an unheard of, and almost incredible manner. In so much that in the <hi>moneth of Aprill</hi> certain Swedish Troops under the command of <hi>Major Generall Arentson</hi> fell into the <hi>Southern Ditmarsh,</hi> and used the inhabitants as bad as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going troops had done: Which new attempts and agreevances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly contrary to the articles of peace, were notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119122:18"/> born withall, till such time, as it were seen, what answer, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and course the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> would take therein, unto whom the complaints thereon were made.</p>
            <p>Besides all which, the <hi>Swedish Commissioners</hi> who were deputed towards the setling of new orders, to wit, how and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner their soulders should be treated till the <hi>First day of May</hi> (for according to the articles of agreement they were not any longer to be entertained) made so many difficulties, as that they would come to no conclusion, which is likewise laid to their charge, as a particular aggrievance quite contrary to the article of agreement.</p>
            <p>And although by the King of Swedens letters dated at <hi>Gotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh</hi> on the 26 <hi>of Aprill,</hi> under his own signature, and seal, and the declaration which was published in the beginning of May, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>King of Swedens</hi> orders to the Lord <hi>Admirall Wrangell,</hi> it was conceived and hoped, <hi>that the swedish solders should be thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards kept under a good discipline, should forbear the said former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, and should immediately be drawn of and march away;</hi> yet shortly after the said Swedes did again impose a rigorous execution <hi>on Kremper-Marsh</hi> for their pretended arrears, in so much that the Danish Guarrisons which lay in <hi>Gluekstadt</hi> and <hi>Crempe</hi> were forced to take their former stations in those parts again, for to hinder and prevent further mischiefs and irruptions.</p>
            <p>Moreover the Swedish <hi>Major Generall Botticher,</hi> in the said <hi>moneth of May</hi> under a pretence of marching away hence by land, passed through the Dominions of <hi>Rensbrough</hi> with 2000 horse, with which in the villages of the said parts, and especially at <hi>Nortdorf</hi> he behaved himself in such an unbeseeming manner, as that the poor people were forced to flye into the <hi>forrests and Woods,</hi> and save themselves, from whom they violently tooke all the horses they could light on, and all their houshould stuff they could lay hands on, killed their Cattell without distinction, and as for <hi>Geese, Hens, Ducks,</hi> and such like Poultry which they had not time to eat, they killed, and nailed upon the doores, and in a most inhumane man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>slew many poor people, as a poor Peasant</hi> who had <hi>seven Children</hi> an <hi>old decreped Woman,</hi> insomuch that a declared profest Enemy could not have done worse.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119122:19"/>
            <p>And about the midst of <hi>June</hi> the Lord <hi>Oxensterns</hi> Squadron be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt 6, and 700 men, and 200 Officers, belonging to the Trayn of artillery, with their servants, and 220 canon-horses did quarter in the <hi>Parish of Nortdorf,</hi> and pretended to remain inquar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd, and to subsist their, till such time, as the whole army should march away, notwitstanding the <hi>King ef Swedens</hi> former exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and freeing of those parts from inquarterings.</p>
            <p>In the same moneth likewise the <hi>Swedish Colonel Gorgas</hi> with the whole regiment drew in <hi>Haslow,</hi> and the Hasslower Marsh, and some Companyes demanded quarters at <hi>Newdorf,</hi> whereon the <hi>Swedish Resident</hi> at <hi>Hamborough,</hi> by name <hi>Moller,</hi> did allot them their quarters there, which concerned him not at all, whereupon the <hi>Kingly Holsteinish Counsellors,</hi> did make complaints thereon to his <hi>Palsegrave,</hi> but to no purpose, and without any effect.</p>
            <p>In the beginn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of June <hi>Major Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eral Bottic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> did again with some Regiments quarter himself in Ditmarsh.</p>
            <p>So likewise <hi>five Swedish Regiments,</hi> namely the <hi>Duke of We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars,</hi> the <hi>Earl of Solms, Colonell Gorga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Collonell Cunstens, and Collonel Shonlehens,</hi> together with the <hi>Squadron of Colonel Smith,</hi> did take up their quarters in the <hi>County of Pinnenbergh,</hi> and forced their maintainance there in an unsupportable manner, not willing to be contented with any thing that was reasonable. The <hi>Duke of Weymers Regiment</hi> alone requiring for every ten dayes <hi>provision</hi> 18730 pound of bred, 10515 pounds of flesh, 107 barrells of beer, 15 quarters of Oats, and 100 Rix dollers in service mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, or else in lieu thereof every ten dayes, 800 Rixdollers, which said summes should they be multiplied according unto the number of the afore specified re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, would in few dayes amount to more then all the poor Inhabitants (who were at that time remaining in their dwellings) were worth, either in corne, substance, or any other goods whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: And whereas the Souldiers, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re so quartered, saw that the country people were not able to provide for them, they fell a cutting down the best and fairest woods, and forrest, selling by hundreds and thousand of tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es together, which they compelled the peasants themselves to carry away, and sell, on the <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> the <hi>Ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> at <hi>Hamborough,</hi> and in other places, whereby they rais<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119122:19"/> great summes of money, which thing also was continued ever since, as long as the Swedes remained in <hi>Holstein</hi> and <hi>Jutland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, against all the Promises made, all the Grants which were given, either in writing or by word of mouth, all the Treaties and Agreements which were concluded on; In the moneth of <hi>July,</hi> several Swedish Regiments did again intrude and force them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seves into the <hi>Wilster</hi> and <hi>Cremper Marsh,</hi> against which neither those Remonstrances which were thereon made unto the King of Sweden himself, and unto the Officers in chief of his Forces, were any wayes valuable, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could in the least redress the same.</p>
            <p>Besides all which <hi>Major General A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enson</hi> did on the 23. of <hi>July</hi> fall into the <hi>Wilster Marsh</hi> with two Regiments, whereby the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistences yet remaining, which the King of Denmarks Guarrisons had out of those parts, were totally withdrawen, all which the King of Denmark was forced in so sad a conjuncture of time to pass, by and suffer; since that no Remonstrances, nor addresses thereon made to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> (amongst which the <hi>King of Denmarks</hi> Letter unto the <hi>Palsgrave of Sultzbach,</hi> marked with the Letter K. is to be comprised) could be considerable, or of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to divert them from these unjust proceedings.</p>
            <p>Finally, wheneas we were in a longing expectation for the return of the aforesaid <hi>Ambassador Cojet,</hi> with the <hi>Ratification</hi> of all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever had been till that time negotiated, and treated on, (whereon chiefly we relyed, and thought our selves secured) the King of Sweden, as then, took his time to put his long since (as it seems) resolved on <hi>hostile invasion</hi> in execution, and under the pretence of his going to <hi>Pomerania</hi> or <hi>Porussia,</hi> with those Forces which in the beginning of the Moneth of August he had embarqued at <hi>Kiel;</hi> the said King (before he had given any notice thereof in the least, or had denounced any war at all) did about the seventh of August unexpectedly and unthought of, fall into he <hi>Isle of Zealand</hi> again, and on the ninth of the said moneth, directly marched towards the Cittie of <hi>Copenhaghen,</hi> surprizing the Danish Horse, which were distributed throughout all the whole Island, and lay dispersed up and down in their quarters; some of which he constrained to take service under him, the rest he detained as Prisoners, and cut off the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119122:20"/> passage of those who would have retired themselves unto <hi>Coppen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haghen,</hi> and proceeded to make his approaches towards the King of Denmarks said place of Residency, which he continued both by day and night, and in like manner possessed himself of the Town <hi>Helsingnur,</hi> and plaid upon the <hi>Castle of Cronenbourgh</hi> from several Batteries.</p>
            <p>Whereupon it must needs consequently follow, that the King of Sweden vilifying the respect which he doth at least owe unto the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> (whereof he is a member) and to the <hi>Emperors Person,</hi> hath (contrary to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Constitutions of the Empire,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Law of Nations,</hi> contrary to the strict and tender <hi>Pacifica ion</hi> of <hi>Munster</hi> and <hi>Osnabourgh,</hi> and especially contrary to the Articles of the Treaty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Peace at <hi>Roschil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) acted al <hi>manner of Hostilities</hi> in the highly considerable, and most important Imperial Fronteer, the <hi>Dutc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hy of Holstein,</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng not satisfied with this, neither having constrained the said <hi>Dutchy</hi> to maintain the <hi>Swedish Army</hi> for a long time, and to furnish them with great and considerable summes of money, But also about the same time (when as he had resolved to fall into <hi>Zealand a ain in a hostile manner</hi>) attempted on a sudden, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly, to surprize and take the strong <hi>Fortresses</hi> of <hi>Glucks<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adt</hi> and <hi>Rensbourgh,</hi> the <hi>Steanbourg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Sconse,</hi> and sev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ral other consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable places: but when they perceived that they had mist of these their designs, they then contented themselves to keep the said places blocked up. Moreover they detained and took Prison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers several of <hi>His Majestie the King of Denmarks</hi> Subjects, both <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> and <hi>Civil Officers,</hi> and a great number of the chief and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Gentry and Citizens, who thought themselves very secure, and were some of them in their respective homes, in their Countrey houses, and some of them on journeys, on their own private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerments; divers of which the said Swedes have sent away out of the Land; as also they surprized the <hi>King of Denmarks Life-guard of Horse,</hi> commanded by the <hi>Field Marshall Everstein,</hi> which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment was dispersed in their quarters in the <hi>Marsh Lands,</hi> and who had kept good Correspondency with those <hi>Swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> which lay inquartered in the like manner joyntly with them; wounding se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the said Regiment Officers, taking others Prisoners, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119122:20"/> enforcing the private Soldiers to serve under them; Moreover they did set upon the <hi>House Haselow</hi> in a hostile manner, and made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected attempts upon several other Forts and Places, some of which under the pretence of amitie and Friendship they mastered, but were driven away with bloody heads, and with the loss of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of their men, (which they left dead behinde them,) from such places as took timely notice of this their violating the peace, in so unjust and horrid a manner, as that it must needs be odious both to God and Men.</p>
            <p>And in like manner between the 8. and 9. of <hi>August, a Royal Swedish Fleet</hi> unexpectedly, and on a sudden, appeared before this Town and Haven of <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> and in a hostile manner im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaded the egress and regress from and to the same, and did ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest and seaze <hi>Duke John Frederick</hi> of <hi>Brunswick and Lunenbourgh</hi> the <hi>Queen of Denmarks Brother,</hi> who had nothing to do with this cause, and who was to be considered as a <hi>Free Prince</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> yet <hi>they detained both Him and the Ship, wherein he was minded to have come hither,</hi> and <hi>several</hi> other <hi>Ships and Merchandizes</hi> in like manner; not giving any hearing or credit to the <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petter,</hi> who was by the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> sent to the said <hi>Duke,</hi> not so much as permitting him to see the said <hi>Duke,</hi> but kept the said <hi>Trumpetter</hi> shut down in the hold of the said Ship so strictly, as that he could not be spoken unto by any of the said Dukes ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>Moreover they surprized and seized several of the <hi>King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks men of War,</hi> and other ships, together with all their equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, ships company, and Marriners, <hi>who relying upon the Peace,</hi> and thinking themselves secure, not expecting any Enmity or acts of Hostility, were riding safe, as they thought, in the <hi>Sound,</hi> in the <hi>Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> before <hi>Christiana,</hi> and <hi>in other Harbors or Havens,</hi> as also those which lay at <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>use,</hi> and in the <hi>Harbor</hi> of <hi>Christianstadt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loden with the <hi>King of Denmarks Ordnance, Ammunitions</hi> and <hi>Provisions,</hi> with the which they were on their return, to bring them into the <hi>Kingdom of Denmark,</hi> in reference unto the afore <hi>specified Articles of Peace;</hi> which said ships with their Ladings, as aforesaid, the Swedes carried away, fell upon them unawares,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119122:21"/> and made them good prize: to wit, 1. <hi>The Pellican.</hi> 2. <hi>The Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</hi> 3. <hi>The Sea lease.</hi> 4. <hi>The S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arren Seuen.</hi> 5. <hi>The Galliot called the Hope.</hi> 6. <hi>The St. George.</hi> 7. <hi>The Hunter.</hi> 8. <hi>A Dunke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k Booyer</hi> and several others, whereby it may be evidntly observed, that after they had detained at <hi>Bahuse</hi> and <hi>Christiana</hi> afore specified, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Ordnances, Ammunitions and Provisions, and that a part of them were a little before brought on board of the said ships, they as then, just when the said ships were ready to set sail towards <hi>Denmark,</hi> did commence <hi>this their breach of Peace,</hi> insomuch as that thereby they obtained (as a booty and prey) not only those par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which were loden on board the said Vessels, and which were brought out of the said <hi>Fortresses,</hi> but also all the Artillery, ammunitions, and provisions, and other necessaries belonging to <hi>His said Majesty,</hi> and the which were as yet undelivered, so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they detained and made use of all the Vessels and Boats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the inhabitants of <hi>Funen, Jutland</hi> and <hi>Holstein,</hi> all this whole Summer, against all equity, justice, and against the Treaty of Peace, forcing them to make several voyages for, and with them into <hi>Livonia, Porussia</hi> and <hi>other parts,</hi> and finally made them of good prize, whereby the <hi>Navigation, Trading</hi> and <hi>Commerce</hi> of those parts fell to the Ground, and the inhabitants were thereby totally ruined, and like to perish and starve.</p>
            <p>Moreover it is worthy to be observed, how that the afore named <hi>Swedish Ambassador Cojet,</hi> after he had been treated with all the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities and curtesies imaginable, being departed with entire sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, did never testifie a greater amity and a more true and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all well grounded affection on the behalf of the <hi>King his Master</hi> then at his departure hence on the third of <hi>August,</hi> even in such an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner, as that he proceeded so farr, as to <hi>motion a match</hi> between <hi>his Highnesse the Prince of Denmarke, and the Duke of Gottorps Lady daughter,</hi> in the which he profered to be a <hi>Mediator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whilst that we were in an earnest expectation to receive all these good tydings at his hands, behold him active on board of the hostile <hi>Fleet before Coppen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> writing and sending letters thence to his Colleague the Swedish Senator and present Ambassador in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119122:21"/> this place, the <hi>Lord Steno Bielke,</hi> and without doubt also hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven good advise both to the <hi>King of Sweden,</hi> and his <hi>Admirall,</hi> of the concernments and particulars of this place, which must needs be sufficiently known unto him, he having for the space of four moneths constantly resided therein.</p>
            <p>Moreover the said <hi>Lord Bielke</hi> did make provision of sundry weapons and fire-armes in his lodgings in this citty, as also encreas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the number of his servants and attendants, protesting however that he knew nothing in the least of this suddain and hostile inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and most earnestly besought <hi>His Majesty the King of Denmarke</hi> to redouble those guards, which he had ordained to attend upon him, to have a care of his security, seeing the <hi>common people</hi> were very ill satisfied with him, supposing that the said Ambassador under the notion of friendship should have fomented the like <hi>hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile councills and actions,</hi> and therefore threatned him. Whereupon the <hi>King of Denmarke</hi> did cause him to be safely conducted into his <hi>Majesties</hi> own house, situated in his garden called <hi>Rosin bourough</hi> and thereto be lodged in all manner of safety, since there could not a better nor securer place be found to put the said Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor into. And who being several times interrogated in his Majesties name on the premisses, did continually declare and most solemnly protest, that he knew not any thing at all concerning the <hi>King of Swedens hostile designe nor invasion of Denmarke.</hi> And just upon the nick of this attempt and invasion, the <hi>Swedes</hi> had caused to be published through the whole world (with a great deal of craft and falsehood) and Printed it in the <hi>publicke Corrantos,</hi> or <hi>News-Books that there were great differences and misunderstandings fallen out betwixt his Majestie the King of Denmark, and some of his great Lords and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, insomuch as that they had conspired against his Majesty the Kings life, where by his Majesty was constrained to demande assistance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the King of Sweden against this rebellious subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And some <hi>Swedish Officers,</hi> who at the beginning of this breach of peace arrived with their troops at Koke in Zealand, did report and divulge, that the <hi>King of Swedens designe was not against the King of Denmarks Person, or Kingly goverment, but was chiefly undertaken against severall of his disaffected Rebellious, and disloyall subjects.</hi> Of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119122:22"/> all which there was no mention made in the least in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> nor had there any such thing hapned, insomuch that this <hi>Knacke</hi> must needs passe for a meere <hi>Swedish invention,</hi> whereby they expected to reape a great benefit: although it is well known to all the world, <hi>that all his Majestie of Denmarks subjects and provinces, are more loyall and true unto him, then the Swedes could wish or desire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, so soon as the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> had notice of the <hi>hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile invasion</hi> of the <hi>Isle of Zealand on the</hi> 8 <hi>of August,</hi> his Majesty did depute towards the <hi>King of Sweden two of his Senators,</hi> the <hi>Lord Moyens Hogh, and Christian She,</hi> who met the said <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead,</hi> within eight leagues of this place on <hi>the ninth of August,</hi> but could not be addmitted to a hearing or audience untill the next day after, because it was too late on the preceeding day.</p>
            <p>When as, after the usuall complements had taken place, it was represented to the said <hi>King; That he must needs remember, that the foregoing differences and misunderstandings which were come to an open breach and war betwixt the two Northern Crowns, were by Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and through the mediation of the most Christian King of France, and of his Highnesse the Lord Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland, composed and were brought to a firme and reall peace, all things being setl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again in their form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r beings, an absolute act of oblivion past, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenor of the concluded on agreement of Roschilt, were so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly described, sealed, ratified, and mutually desined by both parties. And when as afterwards there was occasion for any additional treaties to the better clearing of certain particulars in question, the same demands where by the King of Denmarke consented and agreed unto, in such a manner as (if the treaty had been well handled) that either the one or the other might have been accepted, or rejected, so that there was not any thing left unsetled, all things meeting with their desired ends. But if any difference remained or were to be moved concerning the booty made at Guinea, it might have been considered, that both the sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commissioners were agreed, What and how much the Crown of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke should pay in lieu thereof, whereunto also the king of Denmarke, had consented, the businesse only sticking upon the time, and the assurance, to wit, when the said summe should be payed, and in what manner the payment of the moneys should remain assured: And whereas the Swedish
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119122:22"/> Ambassador Coyet, had taken upon himself to settle that busines with the King of Sweden, and to that purpose was a few dayes since de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted hence towards his Majestie, it was conceived on our parts, that the said businesse was in like manner settled and effected, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that after such a settling of affaires the King of Denmarke thought it very strange to be invaded both by water and Land, in such a clandestine manner, and in so suddain and unexpected away, without any reason at all given, or preceeding denuntiation of war, That it was deemed an Act beneath the generosity of the King of Sweden, to violate the Articles of peace so earnestly presecuted, and so strictly confirmed, both by his Majesties hand and seale, That it was rather believed the King of Swedens fortunes and progresses were to be steered by Justice and equity, in such a manner as that the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le world might not be able to speak ill of them, seing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the King of Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehalf all the granted Provinces and fortresses, as also all the troops, and other things agreed on, were complyed withall, whereunto on this side, there was not any engagment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme: With a further assurance that the King of Denmarke, did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire any ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er thing save peace, quietnesse and friendship with the King of Sweden, and to obser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and keep the same. Moreover that the said, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators were sent unto his Majesty to no other end, save to take of all those suspicion and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elousie, which it seemed were at hand, and therefore humbly supplicated his said Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esty to appoint Commissioners, unto whom they would clearly demonstrate, that the King their Master had not in the least given any occasion of Enmity, far lesse of any rupture or breach, and that he had not so much as harbored the least thought thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto all which the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> himself did most amply make answer, and beginning with all the transactions which happened as well before, as since the last warr, between the two <hi>Northern Crowns,</hi> he repeated the same, as also whatsoever else is contained in the Northern Histories, and had hapned for severall years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but especially and particularly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Crown of Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> had endeavored the <hi>King of Swedens, and his Kingdoms</hi> ruine, and had first of all given him cause of provocation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they had endeavored to undermine and diminish the commerce and traffick of Sweden.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119122:23"/>
            <p n="3">3. That they had not observed the particulars, which they had yeelded unto by the pacification of Roschiltd: Nor reflecting on the King of Swedens slacking the course of his victories, purposely to hinder the ruine of the King of Denmarks family, and of his Crown, which he deferred, relying upon the performance of the treaty betwixt them. That he had understood since, the Danes only sought occasion to deferr and detain him in his proceedings, that therefore he could not withdraw his forces out of their Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That letters from Denmarke which are extant, and had been sent to England, and others which were written from Holland by the King of Denmarks Extraordinary deputy, the Lord <hi>Henry Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemsen Resenvinge,</hi> gave a sufficient evidence of the <hi>Danish designes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The King likewise complained of what had hapned in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains of Druntheim, with late Peter Wieben, concerning Rumbs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, where he was detayned by the King of Denmarke.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He complained likewise that the Crown of Denmarke had not dealt well with his Father in Law, the Duke of Sleswigh, Got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top and Holstein, but had also deferred and delayed him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That Denmarke would not joyne in an alliance with Sweden, when as the King of Sweden desired but 8, or 10, ships for his assistance, whereby his designes were hindred, and his field pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, whereunto his Councill had advised him, was totally neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and lost, so that he was resolved to commit the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of this his undertaking to God, and his good fortune, for the which the King of Denmarke had given him occasion by writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of letters to his Allyes, only to breed delayes and to gain time and to receive such forces, as were for that purpose expected out of <hi>Holland,</hi> thereby to be in a capacity to stand upon his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Finally, the said King complained, that the person who had brought away the booty from <hi>Guinea,</hi> had not been arrested and detained.</p>
            <p>Whereunto the King of <hi>Denmarke Ambassadors and senators</hi> reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That allthough severall acts of hostility had hapned since the denunciation of the warr, yet however the same were passed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119122:23"/> forgotten and buryed in silence, by vertue of the <hi>solemn rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Peace,</hi> and by <hi>the act of oblivion,</hi> which was accordingly passed on all sides: <hi>Hoping that as yet his said Majestie would not reject any reasonable Treaties or overtures, and that also those prejudiciall let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to, and from Allyes, might be produed,</hi> since they knew not in the least any thing concerning the same.</p>
            <p>And when as the foregoing delayes, and detentions, were seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times and often urged as the <hi>chief causes</hi> of this new Enmity and acts of Hostility, there was returned in answer thereunto, that the <hi>Swedish Ambassadors</hi> themselves were the cause thereof: That those affaires which had been debated and assented unto by the <hi>Treaty at Coppenhaghen,</hi> were in themselves matters of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, cheifly those things, which the King of Sweden both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired and obtained for himself, and for <hi>Duke Frederich of Slegwigh, Holstin and Gottorp,</hi> as namely the yielding up of all the Territories and the Kingly priviledges, wherein they had reason to expect some moderation, since there was no prefixt time setled, within which the said Treaties should be concluded; moreover that it was apparent, that some part of the said Articles, notwithstanding they were assented unto by both parties, as also accepted of by the Commissioners and Deputies of the interessed Parties, and were accordingly set down in writing; yet nevertheless the same Articles were on the behalf of the <hi>Swedes</hi> annulled, and revoked upon this bare pretence only, that they were not acceptable, nor did at all please the <hi>King of Sweden:</hi> And whereas the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> had complyed with, and absolutely performed, whatsoever he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged unto; yet on the behalf of the King of Sweden there was not any thing at all, or very little effected, of what ought to have been done on his part, whereby the burdensome and untollerable delays which were caused, and the deferrings which were urged, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and in effect, far more to be imputed unto the <hi>Swedes</hi> themselves then unto <hi>His Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estie of Denmark.</hi> So likewise was it manifest to all the world, that Denmark at that time was brought to so low an Ebe, as that it was impossible forher, as then, to set out so many ships to sea.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the King of Sweden himself with a great deal of eanestness made a Reply to all the said imputations, and mean
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119122:24"/> while remitted the <hi>King of Denmarks Senators,</hi> and <hi>Ambassadors,</hi> to his <hi>Counsellors,</hi> to see whether they could finde any remedie therein; but when as they declared, that they rather sought to have to do <hi>with the Head (meaning the King himself)</hi> he then asked them, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they intended to put themselves under his protection?</hi> whereunto they answered: That they would willingly know, in the Name, and on the behalf of <hi>His Majestie their King, whether or no this new begun Enmity, and hostile invasion, by the Swedes, might not be modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and appeased.</hi> That there was little or no regard to be had to their own Protection; <hi>but that they requested Commissioners might be appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ends afore specified; and when as they did again most instantly press the same, they were twice told, they had leave to depart.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto there was added: <hi>That the Swedish Ambassador which had been at Coppenhaghen, Sir Julius Coyet, had no power to terminate the Guinea business, but ought to have made his Addresses thereon unto the King his Master.</hi> Now, whereas the <hi>King of Denmarks Senators</hi> did hereby perceive, that the appointing of Commissioners to treat with them was absolutely denyed; they took their leaves, making this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation: <hi>That there was a just God in Heaven, unto whom they would recommend this Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And immediately after, it was notified unto the said <hi>Danish Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators,</hi> whilst they were in their Lodgings; that in case they had any thing else to declare, the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> had appointed the <hi>Lord Marshal Oxenstern,</hi> and the <hi>Earl of Slippenbag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as Commissioners to treat with them;</hi> who also immediately came to them, and after several Proposals, Replies, and Debates, the Danish Senators per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting in their former allegations, and maintaining that the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish newly undertaken Hostilities, were on their side and behalfs, far more grounded on suspitions and Jealousies, then rea ities or effects, and that the afore mentioned pretended delays were not to be admitted of, as sufficient occasions for the breach of a Peace; in regard that those things, which only remained unperfected, and were in a manner finished, were by the Swedish Ambassadors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves undertaken to be moderated, and that the retarding of the same was chiefly to be imputed to themselves, seeing that as afore said, the whole was in a manner concluded on, and brought to a final end.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119122:24"/>
            <p>As then, the Earl of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> after a long Discourse did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <q rend="inline">That <hi>Denmark,</hi> by the afore mentioned pretended and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Delays, had given occasion, that the <hi>Poles,</hi> the <hi>Muscovites,</hi> and the Elector of <hi>Brandenbourgh,</hi> were joyned and reinforced against the <hi>SWedes,</hi> and had hastned the Election of the Roman Emperour, all which the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> could otherwayes have hindred, that it was not unknown how pretious a thing Time was, which (as one before had alledged) could not be recalled by the Almighty himself; and that as <hi>Denmark</hi> might at present see its ruine drawing nigh, and the fatal moment of its subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion hanging over its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead, so the best and most convenient wayes to help themselves, were the rather to be chosen; that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was already Master of the whole Land, and that he would have likewise, the Fortresses and strong places; that therefore it would be as good for the inhabitants to have a King whose name is <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> as one who is named <hi>Frederick,</hi> or was called <hi>Christian;</hi> that there is a God, who doth take away, and give Kingdoms to whom he pleases. and it seems that <hi>Denmarks</hi> fatal hour was at hand. But hower he would pray to God, that so noble and glorious a Cittie as <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> with so many thousands of inhabitants, might not swelter and perish in their own blood.</q> That the Swedes were resolved, first to make themselves Masters of the whole Kingdom, and afterwards to dispute and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Justice of the Cause.</p>
            <p>And in this wise, the said <hi>Danish Senators, and Ambassadors,</hi> were constrained to depart from the said <hi>Swedish Commissioners,</hi> without the effecting of their business, or doing any good with them; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning towards <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> where they arrived on the <hi>eleventh of the said moneth of August,</hi> and gave an ample account of all the aforesaid proceedings to the King of Denmark their Master.</p>
            <p>So that it is remitted to the censure and judgement of all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, sincere, upright, and judicious men, whether or no the Peace which was bought at so dear a rate, and so fully complyed withall, on the behalf of his <hi>Majestie the King of Denmark</hi> can be forfeited by the foregoing arguments urged by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and whether the <hi>Swedes</hi> on the bare allegation of some special pretences, to ground
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119122:25"/> their said quarrel on, without any preceeding notification, when as there was not so much as one Clause of the Treaty left unsatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, can, meerly for a <hi>fond reason of State,</hi> change the everlasting Peace so fully ratified, flrst into a five moneths oppressure, and extortion of the poor inhabitants, and present<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y afterwards into an open war, and into <hi>so grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a bath of blood, as the Earl of Slippen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach threatens the Citty of Coppenhaghen wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all?</hi> So likewise will it be needless to lay open and debate the foregoing Swedish Allegations, seeing <hi>His Majestie the King of Denmarks afore named Senators,</hi> have already, on good grounds, at large, and to the purpose, answered the same; as also, by reason it doth appear, (as clere as the Sun at Noonday) by the afore mentioned allegations exhibited by the Swedes, that <hi>their intention and drift is under a colourable feigned pretence,</hi> to involve the Crown of Denmark in a new War, and to take their time, when as the said King and Kingdom had put themselves out of all postures of defence, living very securely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying upon God and upon the Peace agreed on, to overrun the said Kingdom, and (according to the Earl of <hi>Slippenbachs</hi> aforesaid dreamed of fatality, and by his own supposed decreed of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) first to make themselves Master of this Kingdom, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to dispute the justice of the cause.</p>
            <p>And amongst the rest of the seeming reasons, which the Swedes make use of, to palliate this their hostile unexpected undertaking against all right, and against the Law of Nations, as also against the sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cial Covenants of both the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>T ey alledg this, as if the King of Denmarks intentions against Sweden were made apparent by several intercepted Letters, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his <hi>Majestie the King of Denmark to England,</hi> and <hi>by others written to his said Majestie from Holland, by his extraordinary Deputy there, the Lord Henry Willemsen R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>senvinge, the contents whereof</hi> (as they pretend) <hi>proved very prejudicial to the King of Sweden</hi> (some of which Letters were in a forcible manner taken from the Post of <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> but on <hi>the eighth of August last past</hi>) and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was constrained to make this invasion.</p>
            <p>Which Enterprise, as it was in it felf unjust, so it was attempted after the said Swedish Hostile, resolved on invasion, was already
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119122:25"/> put in execution, yet that all men may clearly see, and judge with the better grounds of this fact, <hi>whether or no the King of Denmarks Letters to his Agent residing at London, the Honourable Simon de Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kum (dated only on the sixth of August last past, and wherein his Majestie gave him a bare information of what had passed since the late Pacification)</hi> could with any reason or equity have moved the King of Sweden to such an extremity, the Contents of the faid Letter is hereafter annexed, marked with the Letter L. and had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in this place, but that it is held unnecessary, and as loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some as chewed meat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover, how could this writing into Enland with equity be alledged as a cause of these hostile attempts, in case there were any thing therein contained, which might tend to the giving of any offence? since the same came not to the King of Swedens hands, until the long since Warlike pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations were made, and that the King of Sweden, with his hostile Troops, was come into Zealand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, there were no other Letters sent by the King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark to England, save one, in the moneth of March, to the Lord Protector, by which an account was given to his late Highness of the <hi>late peace at Rotsc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilt,</hi> and friendly thanks were returned, for his late Highness's interposition and mediation therein, which Letter was sent along with his said Highness extraordinary Envoy, at his return, insomuch as that the Swedes can never produce any other of his <hi>Majesties</hi> Letters unto those parts, since there were no other written.</p>
            <p>And for as much as concerns the writing <hi>of his said Majesties Deputy in Holland, the Lord Rosenving,</hi> as the said Letters have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been produced, nor till this very time, never were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to his <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie the King of Denmark,</hi> so the contents of the same must needs be unknown to him, and cannot in any wise be prejudicial unto the <hi>King of Sweden,</hi> since in such a cas, they would not have sticked to make them publike. However, it is not to be presumed, that the said <hi>Extraordinary Deputy</hi> (whose good conduct and sincerity is sufficiently known) would in his said Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have inserted any thing, save that, which might be answerable and becoming a <hi>good Minister of State, and a faithful Patriot.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119122:26"/>
            <p>And least the misinformed may conceave, that the Swedes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating of the <hi>King of Denmarks</hi> having ill dealt with <hi>Duke Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick of Sleswigh, Holstein, &amp;c.</hi> may pass for a new ground of a Quarrel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majestie of Denmark</hi> knoweth nothing hereof in the least, nor hath the said <hi>Duke Frederick</hi> ever made any complaints thereon, and the contrary will easily appear by the several friendly Letters, Messages, Answers, Deputations, and the amicable Contestations which hath passed between them.</p>
            <p>For before the said Swedish hostile designes brake forth, and were known to the King of Denmark: by reason of the urgency and necessity of his affairs, he deputed his <hi>Counseller, Governour, and High Bayliff of Rensbourgh, the Lord Henry Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men, Knight</hi> to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> said <hi>Duke Frederick,</hi> with the annexed Letter marked M, and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> annexed instructions marked N, by which the particular confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which <hi>His Majestie</hi> reposed in the said <hi>Duke</hi> doth appear: As also by his requesting the said <hi>Dukes</hi> interposition, in the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto a quiet and peaceable condition, which he promiseth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe from the said Duke.</p>
            <p>But how real and upright the Swedish intentions have been, as concerning the said often specified Peace, and in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at manner the same hath been observed and kept by them, not only the <hi>King of Denmarks</hi> Subjects in <hi>Holstein, Jutland,</hi> and <hi>Funen,</hi> to their ruine and undoings, have sadly experimented; but also the inhabitants of <hi>Norway,</hi> who were also comprized in the said everlasting Peace, suffered as much as the others.</p>
            <p>And not to specifie those passages which have hapned in the Provinces which the <hi>King of Denma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> by the said Peace did make over and resign to the Swedes: we shall only touch upon the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of <hi>Shonen</hi> and <hi>Bleckingen,</hi> where all the young and able men, were inregistred, and by constraint were sent away unto Livonia, Porussia, Pomerania, and unto the rest of the Swedish Provinces and guarisons, there to serve in the wars.</p>
            <p>All which being evident and manifest, it is the more to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, how the <hi>Swedish Resi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent Gustue D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wall,</hi> who was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioned to reside in the <hi>Sound,</hi> (during the amicable and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119122:26"/> treaties with the King of Swedens Ambassadors, should dare to averre and say, that he was deputed expresly one the behalf of his Master, to the augmenting, and establishing of an entire confidence, reall amity, and all kind of neighbourly good offices betwixt both the said kings, their Kingdomes, Countries, and Subjects, when as the Swedish actions do quite and clean contradict these professions and protestations. The which is dayly more and more apparent, seeing it is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ifest how and in what manner, since this their newly begun and continued open breach of the peace, they demean themselves (no body giving them the least occasion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) beyond all reason and humanity, <hi>in the Country of Pinnen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh, in the Dukedomes of Sleswigh a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Holstein, in a most unchistian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like barbourousway, and after the Tartarian manner, by fire und flame, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligings, devastations, murderings, and defacing, raveanging, and sackag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countreys in such a wise, as that it can hardly be described in writing; and particularly by the burning and destroying of the best part of the Domaine of Pennenbergh, besides the Castle and whatsoever lyeth between Elmes-horn and Ute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>son, situated beyond the Awe, and the whole Marsh thereabouts, the domaine and towne of Segebery, the territories belonging to the Earle of Rantzow, namely Rake, and the parts adjacent, the Noble dwelling and Knightly seat Haseslow, Haselderf, and Cahden, the Cloister and village of Uterson, the towne of Brouns-buttell in Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marsh, Edelacke in Hertz-horn, Newdorf, divers houses in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster marsh, and severall other places, which they have horredly abused and defaced, besides the beautifull towne of Itzohoe, together with the Cloyster, which they had before reduced to ashes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the whole inhabitable judicious world, whether they be friends or foes,</hi> may by the aforementioned true relation, evidently perceive, that such like proceedings as these, and the afore specified hostile invasion of Denmarke by the Swedes, doth altogether oppugne the former agreements, and the articles of peace, and chiefly, is quite and cleane contrary to the first article of the same, by the which it was evidently and clearly agreed upon, and before all other things most solemnly ratified.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">That from hence forwards betwixt both Kings, a firm ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting and irrevocable peace is established, and that all forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119122:27"/> misintelligences, war, and enmity, are laid a side, and that for the future a generall act of oblivion shall be passed, and a set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led friendship and neighbourhood, shall be established and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, in such a maner, as that both the said Kings are thereby reciprocally obliged, and engaged, to endeavour each others pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, benefit and welfare, both to farther, and improve the same. Even also in all things, which may concerne the aforesaid Kings persons, goverments, kingdomes, jurisdictions or subjects, so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise should they endeavour to divert, to the utmost of their powers, all the losses prejudices, and damages, which might happen or befall their, or either of their Persons, as by the afore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> specified article annexed and comprised under the Letter O, may more amply appear, according to the contents of the same.</q> As also in conformity to the peace which was afterwards concluded on <hi>betwixt the two said Kings of Denmarke and Sweden, at Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike-bourgh,</hi> and by their personall amicable plighted communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion together, from the 3, to the 5 th. of March last past, as also by their reall relying upon each others speciall friendship, and by the demonstrations of their brotherly love.</p>
            <p>Moreover by their enterchanged letters, under their own hand writings (which 'ere long will also be published) and finally by the said King of Swedens so often reiterated Professions, and Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of friendship, both by word of mouth and by his written letters.</p>
            <p>In conclusion, By all the foregoing proceedings, it is manifest that on the Swedish part, no other thing could be discerned, save that they (by a naturall hatred to peace and quietnesse) have aymed at no lesse, then to finde out an invention, to withdraw themselves from, and to relinquish the absolute and compleat en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire agreement, and the articles of Peace, which on both sides were consented, and agreed unto, with so much solemnity and integrity ratified by both parties, and which on the part of the King and Crown of Denmark was so punctually and religiously observed, and in all the points thereof performed, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also that the said agreement <hi>was on the publick faith, by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious, endeavers, and interposition of his most Christian Majesties
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119122:27"/> Ambassador, and His Highness the Lord Protector's of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Ireland's Extraordinary Envoy, mediated and concluded; as also by them subscribed, and sealed,</hi> as it doth more amply appear by the annexed Clause under the Letter P. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/>
            </p>
            <p>Upon all which there can no other opinion be harboured, nor judgement passed by persons of unbyassed, unprepossest, unpassio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and worthy mindes, save that the Swedes, through a vehement desire to purchase and subvert forreign Kingdoms, as also with a designe to subvert and destroy this said kingdom of Denmark, and so being Masters of the same, to attain unto the sole and entire Dominion of the <hi>Baltick Sea;</hi> to the manifest prejudice of all those, who are interressed and, engaged in the Traffick, and commerce, of those parts; Moreover by degrees to extend their Forces against the rest of the Neighbouring Princes, by the enlarging of their own Dominions, have undertaken this present violation of the Peace, and thereon made this present invasion of Denmark.</p>
            <p>Yet however we do trust on the Lord, and rely on the justice of our Cause, since we know our selves innocent, and guiltless before him, (as well as before all the World) That on our parts the least wilful, express, just, or sufficient Cause, hath not been given to beget a new rupture and dissention; Putting our entire confidence in God: <hi>That he will stand by, and aid His Majestie of Denmark, our gracious King, by a powerful hand and outstretched Arm.</hi> All Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Kings, Princes, Potentates, Commonwealths and States, who are any wise interressed with the Swedes, allyed unto them by Treaties, Obligations or Promises, either in the nature of Friends, or Foes, having their eyes as now sufficiently opened by the Swedes themselves, may perceive by these before related proceedings of the <hi>Swedes against Denmark,</hi> how far they may rely and trust to their former Treaties, and Agreements with them, as also to their feigned Friendship, or to their already proffered, or to be proffered Covenants, or Promises; and how great cause all men have to stand upon their own guards, and to apprehend, that in case the Swedes (setting aside, and not regarding all the respects due to Honour, Honesty, and Probity) shall be permitted to take their time (when as they shall have pretended to have calculated, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119122:28"/> foreseen the approaching destruction and fatal Destiny of Forreign Kingdoms, Principalities, States, Commonwealths, and Nations) to overrun and master the same.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Coppenhaghen</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 29. <hi>September,</hi> Anno 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>The annexed Extract of such Articles of the Pacification, and other Letters specified in the foregoing Relation, as do conduce to the better understanding of the same, and whereunto Reference is made according to the Marginal Alphabetical Letters. viz.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>A. Page</hi> 2. Extract of the Treaty of Peace betwixt the <hi>Kings of Denmark and Sweden,</hi> made at <hi>Reschilt,</hi> the 26. of <hi>February. Anno</hi> 1657./1658.</head>
               <p>ANd to the end that the evacuation, and enterchanging of the before mentioned Provinces, Towns, and strong places may the better be effected on both sides, both parties have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that so soon as the 2000 horse (which the <hi>King of Denmark</hi> hereby acknowledgeth to deliver to the <hi>King of Sweden</hi>) shall be so delivered; the Swedish army shall immediately march out of <hi>Zealand,</hi> after which, <hi>Helsenbourgh</hi> shall be yielded up on the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119122:28"/> 27. of <hi>February, Landscron</hi> on the 28. and <hi>Malmeu</hi> on the first of <hi>March:</hi> On the 4. of the same moneth <hi>Christianstadt</hi> shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Swedish Plenipotentiaries; and on the same day <hi>Naxchan</hi> shall be yielded to the Danish Commissioners; at which time a so, the Swedish Army shall march out of <hi>Laland, Falster,</hi> and <hi>Langland.</hi> On the 15 of <hi>March,</hi> the delivering of <hi>Christianopel</hi> in <hi>Blecking,</hi> as also of <hi>Bornholm</hi> shall be effected, in case it be possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the weather will permit the same. So likewise <hi>shall Bahuse</hi> be yielded up on the 28: and on the first of <hi>May, Druntheim, Yempterland,</hi> and <hi>Bremerfeurd,</hi> together with all the other places, which, during the time of the war, were taken by the <hi>King of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> (in what parts soever they shall or may be situated) shall be restored to the Swedish Commissioners; in regard whereof all the <hi>King of Swedens</hi> Army shall, on that very day, begin to march out of <hi>Funen, Jutland, Sleswigh, Holstein, Stormar,</hi> and <hi>Ditmarsh;</hi> as also out of all Islands, Fortresses, Noblemen, and Gentlemens Houses whatsoever, by what Names, or Appellations they are known, or called; and on the same day, <hi>viz.</hi> the first of <hi>May,</hi> the strong places of <hi>Fredericks Odde, Pinnenberg, Halsconse,</hi> and all other places, wheresoever they shall, or may be situated, which during the wars are fallen into the possession of the Swedes, shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delivered unto the Danish Commissioners: And at the same time likewise, the Island of <hi>Alsen,</hi> with <hi>Sunderbourgh,</hi> and <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh,</hi> shall be quitted and resigned to their right owners: In the same manner, all whatsoever, within the said Kingdoms, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Dukedoms, and Islands, shall be found to have been taken by either Party, shall be restored and delivered to the right Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in the same manner, as if the same were expresly mentioned, and specified herein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119122:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>B. Page</hi> 3. Extract of the said Pacification. <hi>Artic.</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>TO the end likewise, that the Inhabitants be not oppressed or forced to any unreasonable thing, at the time of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing the said Fortresses, or the drawing off of the Souldiery, out of the Provinces, and Towns, at the prefixed, and limited times, Commissioners on both sides shall be present, who shall take a special care, that nothing shall be taken away from the Inhabitants by force, nor suffer any injury to be offered unto them. And whereas, the Swedish Army is to be entertained with their necessary dyet, as long as they are to remain in these parts, so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, all necessary orders, and good discipline shall be observed, and kept therein. Neither shall there any exactions, or impositions of war, of what nature soever, be required of, and forced upon the Inhabitants, save only such accommodations, as the Souldiery shall stand in need of, for their bare maintenance, as long as they are to be in these parts; according to the orders, which shall be hereon setled by the Commissioners appointed thereunto on both sides.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>C. Page <hi>4.</hi> Article the <hi>22.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe King of Denmark shall give reasonable satisfaction, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to equity, unto the Duke of Sleswigh, Holstein and Gottorp; whereupon Commissioners on both sides, (to wit, of the King of Denmarks, and of the said Dukes) shall treat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119122:29"/>
               <head>D <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>Article the</hi> 21.</head>
               <p>THe foregoing treaties, as namely that at Stetin, Sorode, and Bremsbroe, which have been assented unto by both these Crowns, shall remain in full force, and be unalterable in all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their articles, in the same manner, as they were before the beginning of this war, and even as if they were herein resumed, and repeated from word to word, unlesse they should chance to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly altered by this said Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>E <hi>Page</hi> 6. <hi>Article the</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>TO which purpose it is agreed betwixt us, and on both sides Promised, that we shall not permit or suffer any forreigne hostile Fleet of ships (belonging to any whomsoever) to passe through the Sound, or Belt into the Eastern Seas, but that each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye shall on his behalf hinder and oppugne the same, according to all his power and might.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>F <hi>Page</hi> 7. <hi>Article the</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>IN likemanner on the behalf of the King and Crown of Denmark, the Castle and Domain of Bahuz. As also the House and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Druntheim with all the Townes, Castles, and Forts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, and likewise all the Ecclesiasticall and Temporall goods, Offices, and Emoluments, which of right appertain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119122:30"/> and such as formerly have had any dependency on the same, both by water, and by land, are quitted and made over to the King and Crown of Sweden, to remain in Possession of, and unto the said Crown, as an inheritance for ever, according to the tenor of such let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Patents of Resignation, as shall be made thereon, by the said King of Denmark, and his Senators, signed by them both 'in the same forme and tenor as concerning the other lands, and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which are specified in the following article, and are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed accordingly, as by the said Letters Patents more amply ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>G <hi>Page</hi> 13. <hi>Article the</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>ANd as those strong places, which on both sides have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken during this war, as well as those, which by this Treaty of Peace are to be yeilded up, shall be delivered barely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Guns, so likewise it is agreed and concluded, that the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants in the Territories, where such Fortresses and Strong places are situated, shall be bound to transport and carry all the Guns, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitions, and provisions, to such a Shore or coast, whence they shall or may be best put on shipboard and transported.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>H</hi> Page <hi>9.</hi> Coppy of a Letter from the Danish Field Marshall, the Lord Everstein, to the Swedish Major General Botticher, whereby the delivery of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining horse is again and again proffered.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honoured Major Generall.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Received your second letter dated yesterday, wherein you do urge the delivery of 560 horse, and whereunto the annexed letter dated at Gottorp doth relate: I doe very much wonder how
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119122:30"/> you can make your account upon 560 horse, whereas in your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer three letters, you do only say, that you had order to receive but 400 horse, of the 1000, which remained to be delivered unto the King of Sweden. And the rather because the King my Master hath written unto me, that the King of Sweden was content to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the 1000 remaining horse in two regiments under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Colonel Guldenleew, to wit: 500 of them in Jutland, of Colonell Brokenhusens Regiment, and the remaining 500 in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein, That Lieutenant Generall Horn should receive those in Jut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and your self those in Holstein, and therewith to remain sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, which ought accordingly to stand good. I have likewise seen by the said annexed Paper, That the Major Generall is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to demand a specification concerning those horse which are to be delivered about the parts of Gluckstadt, as that they should be all Germain Souldiers and no Danes, nor no Patcht nor ragged men to be slipt in amongst them, but that they might be good men, well mounted, against which there might be no exceptions to be taken; Now whereas there are no horse to be delivered by those of Gluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stadt, but by his Majestie the King of Denmark my Master, I attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to the zeale of the indicture, who rather chose to mention those of Gluckstadt, then to nominate the King my Master. As for my self I was not borne at Gluckstadt, however they are honest men; Nor am I so great a stranger to the world, as that my name should be unknown: And as concerning the Souldry that they should be no Danes but Germains, and especially well hors'd, I do returne this answer, that I doubt not but the King of Sweden as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ver'st in the military discipline, and by reason thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come famous, will in height of discretion be satisfied with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of 500 such horse, as shall be furnished with sutable arms, such as may be warrantable and passable in an armie. In reference whereunto I shall punctually obey my King and Masters command, and am ready to deliver the said 500 horse. Moreover I cannot conceive that there hath been occasion given to treat the whole Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Nation, amidst whom there are as honest men, as amongst other Nations, and unto whose King I am engaged by oath, with such scornfull language, as if there were occasion to shuffell them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119122:31"/> in amongst the rest of the men, and not to produce and proffer them in a publick way: Nor can I perceive by the King of Swedens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions to the Auditor Generall, that he stands upon such harsh formalities. And as Colonel Guldenlow cannot be in two places at once, I must therefore redemand him back again, and I will by an expresse send you word by the first, on what day the said desired 500 horse shall be delivered. Thus much I thought good to returne you by way of answer, committing you to God, remaining, &amp;c. Gluckstadt the 7 of July 1658. P. S. In case it pleaseth the Major Generall the delivery of the said Regiment can be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay against Monday next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>I</hi> Coppy of the King of Swedens Letter to the Palsgrave of Sultzhagh, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the evacuation and clearing of the Territories of Rensbourgh.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarles Gustave</hi> by the Grace of God King of Sweden, &amp;c. After our friendly greeting, &amp;c. You must needs remember what we formerly wrote unto you from <hi>Fredericks bourgh</hi> concerning the Territories of <hi>Rensbourgh:</hi> And whereas the Danish Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, <hi>Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Juel,</hi> at present with us, hath amongst other things lately also exhibited this aggrievance, and complaint, that notwithstand- the Domains of <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sbourgh</hi> are well nigh quite ruined by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going exactions, yet nevertheless they are constrained to be burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with enquarterings and marches. We therefore do once more desire, you will take care, that the said Domains of <hi>Rensbourgh</hi> may be totally freed, as well from those enquarterings, which it seems the Officers have taken upon themselves to make in those parts, at their own pleasure, as also from all other exactions, and oppressions, that so they may entirely enjoy the exemption by us granted. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending unto your care to have the same performed in a more punctual manner and way then formerly, and commending you to God, &amp;c. <hi>Given at Gottenbourgh the</hi> 2. <hi>May. Signed</hi> Charls Gustave.</p>
               <closer>That this Coppy agrees with the Original, I do testifie the same.
<signed>Signed <hi>Ludwigh Sinhgbagh.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119122:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>K</hi> Coppy of a letter written by his Majestie the King of Denmark to the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave of Sultzbach, concerning the cessation of the Swedish Militar oppressions, committed after the ratification of the Peace.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRedrik the third by the grace of God King of Denmark, &amp;c. Heigh borne Prince, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We had well hoped that our subjects after so many, and mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary oppressions should at present have been made pertakers of, and enjoyed that peace, which is concluded between our self, and our freindly Cousen, Brother, and Neighbour, the King of Sweden, but we are constrained to our great greif to understand, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the said King of Sweden, did promise to free all our Marsh-lands and Territories, as also our Domains of Rensbourgh, from all enquarterings whatsoever. Your Lordship hath never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse charged our said Domains therewith, and in like manner that also under pretence of getting in the remaining contributions, you are fallen into our Southern Ditmarsh. Moreover that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the articles of agreement, and the said Pacification, new regiments are inquartered in the here before mentioned Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and that others which do not quarter therein, have not- have notwithstanding exacted their subsistance, and maintainance therein; of which ill treatments and abuses (being contrary to the King of Swedens promises) we are bound to complaine unto him: Meane while we do hereby desire your Lordship, that you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr them from exacting the remainining pretended contributions, which are impossible to be brought in by our subjects, since they are exhausted to the very Skins. That you will free the Marshlands and our Domains of Rensborough from all enquarterings and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actations, and not suffer them to be oppressed with the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of any other forces, save those who have their quarters therein. But that to the contrary you will cause good discipline and Orders to be observed, that so the poor Inhabitants may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119122:32"/> stay at home to follow their vocations, that people may Travel with safety, and that thereby the trade and commerce, may be continued, whereon we shall relye, and commit you herewith to the Allmighties Protection. Given at Coppenhaghen the 31 of March, Anno. 1658.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>L</hi> Coppy of his Majesties the King of Denmarks letter to the Honourable Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon de Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kum, His Agent in England, Residing at London, being dated the <hi>6</hi> of August <hi>1658,</hi> from Coppenhaghen.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRederick the Third, by the Grace of God, King of Denmark, and Norway of the Vandalls, and Gothes, Duke of Sleswigh, Holstein, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Worthy, Trusty, and well beloved: We doubt not but that even in England, all men are of opinion, that in reference unto the late Treaty the withdrawing of the Swedish army out of our Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories should have been performed on the first day of the Moneth of May last past, according unto the contents of the articles of Peace. But whereas they as yet continue, and do remain in our Lands and Territories, to their utter desolation, It may be those who are not acquainted with the true causes thereof, may impute the reasons of the said delayes to us; wherefore we have thought fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to give you an ample information thereon, by the annexed Papers. To the end, that you may withall possible speed make your addresses to his Highnesse the Lord Protector, that the late Peace made between us, and the King of Sweden on the Publick faith, and by the Meditation of the Lord Protector may be observ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and performed, and that our poor subjects (who are exhausted to the last farthing) may not any more be oppressed with contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and exactions. But that the soulderie may be so far drawn off out of our Dominions, as that our Subjects and our selves may enjoy the fruits of the said Peace, since even in the midst of the greatest flames of war, our oppressions were not so great nor bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome, as they are at present, seeing on our parts we have fully
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119122:32"/> complied with all those particulars, which are contained in the Treaty and articles of Peace concluded on at Roschilt, by the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very up of the Provinces of Shonen and Bleking, with all the strong places therein, the Domains of Bahuz, and Druntheim (both which Territories contain the half of the limits of our Kingdome of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) having evacuated and quitted the fortresses of Bremerfeurde having delivered in the 2000 horse, having satisfied and given full content to Duke Fredrike of Sleswigh, Holstein, and Gottorp, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made restitution of the Salt ships and of all their lodings, and besides have fully complyed on our behalfs, with all wharsoever was comprized, and contained, in the articles of Peace, which were made <hi>Rotschilt;</hi> Over and above which we have remitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King of Sweden, the Isle of <hi>Ween,</hi> although the same doth not at all belong unto the <hi>Province of Shonen,</hi> only for Peace, and quietnesse sake, whereas to the contrary on the behalf of the King of Sweden, the Isles of <hi>Fumen, and Langland, all Jutland,</hi> with the principalities of <hi>Sleswigh,</hi> and <hi>Holstein</hi> have not been restored to us, but are at this very present time, most heavily and sadly oppressed, and burthened by the whole body of the Swedish <hi>Fieldarmy,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by severall of the Inhabitants of the said parts have been constrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to desert their habitations, and livings, and to let them run to ruine, and those who are remained in their said dwellings, are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to despair, and must fall under the heavy oppressions, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of the war, so that we cannot as yet imagine, what the end hereof will prove, nor what the issue will be, unlesse the highly valued authority and interposition of the Lord Protector (by whose mediation the Peace was made, and upon whose warrant we were willing to comply with the same) do induce tde King of Sweden to harbour other thoughts, and to quit our Dominions. And in case on the swedish behalf it should be objected that the businesse concerning the <hi>Guine a-booty,</hi> is not yet concluded; however we have profered that satisfaction thereon, which was beyond reason, or equity to be demanded, or expected, notwithstanding the Swedes have not made an end thereof, either of, or on, wherefore they are not to be excused in letting this whole Army lye thus hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon us, after the ratification of Peace, despoyling our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119122:33"/> to the uttermost. and beyond all sence, or considerations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaving us of all our powers, incommings, and revenews. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our absolute will and pleasure, 1. that you make your earnest addresse to the Lord Protector, and move him, as well by his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as ambassadors, to obtain from the King of Sweden, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further delayes his Armies may be drawn of out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Kingdoms, according unto equity and reason, and in reference to the contents of the late Articles of agreement, which we do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise our selves, and do expect an undoubted answer hereunto, and remain, with the continuance of our Kingly favour towards you, &amp;c. Given at our place of residence in Coppenhaghen on the 6 of August 1658.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>M</hi> Coppy of his Majestie the King of Denmarks Letter dated the <hi>6.</hi> of August, <hi>1658.</hi> from Coppenhaghen, to Duke Frederick of Sleswigh, Holstein, &amp;c. to desire him to contribute towards the marching away of the Swedes, and to admit of, and assist therein the Lord <hi>Henry Bluh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> sent by his Majestie to that purpose:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRederick</hi> the third, &amp;c. We have sent the <hi>Honourable Henry Bluhmen</hi> to consult with your <hi>Highness,</hi> and your chief Ministers, how our common Dutchy, and Territories, may be delivered from the untollerable burdens of the enquarterings of the Swedish Forces, and according to the Articles of agreement, once to be freed from them, as also to inform your Highness, on what termes the Treaties here, betwixt our Deputies, and Senators, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixr the King of Swedens Ambassadors, are depending, and how we do conforme our selves thereunto according to all equity, and reason. And moreover to request your Highness, that you would be pleased by a line or two under your owne hand, and by the sending of a Messenger of your own with the same, to contribute by your highly valued interposition, that our Dominions, and Subjects may be preserved from their evident ruine at hand, and may again en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy an assured rest, and peace. And as your own, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d your Subjects interests are herein highly concerned; and that the j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abitants do groan under the burden of the said heavy op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="8 letters">
                     <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119122:33"/> extorsions, weeping vnder the calamity they are in; We therefore do promise our selves, that you will contribute whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lyes in your power, which may conduce towards the procuring of the said Armies departure, and that you will assist our present Counseller, and Deputy, herein; to the end, that he may the better, and more efficaciously represent the same unto the King of Sweden, unto whom We have likewise commanded him, to make it known; As also that he may with more speed attain the effecting of the same, according as the necessity and urgency of the business requires, which Courtesie We shall endeavour to require, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and to thank your Highness for, and therewith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>
                  <hi>N.</hi> Coppie of His Majestie the King of Denmarks Instructions, which He gave to His Deputy sent to the Duke of Gottorp, dated the <hi>6.</hi> of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. <hi>1658.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRederick</hi> the Third, &amp;c. Trusty and well beloved Councellor, We have thought it fit and expedient, once for all, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the freeing of our Dukedoms and Territories from those heavy and intollerable enquarterings, as also to deliver our Marsh Lands (which are appointed, and set aside for the maintenance of our Fortresses and Guarrisons) from those heavy Oppressions, and burdens under which they lye, by the Exactions of those Regiments, which are newly rusht into the same; that so our Guarrisons may not any longer be depriued of their livelyhoods. Committing, and deputing you thereunto, and requiring you to go to <hi>Gottorp,</hi> with these our Letters, the coppie whereof is annexed, and to deliver them, with the usual Complements on our behalf, to Duke <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> with whom you are to negotiate with speed the contents thereof, and to procure of the said Duke, to send somebody with you to the King of Sweden, and to write a Letter to him, which if you cannot obtain, however, we will, that you immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair unto the said King, and deliver unto him our Letter, and at an appointed Audience, after such due Complements, as we leave to your own discretion, to use all possible endeavours with the said King, that the Peace which was lately made betwixt Us and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119122:34"/> said King, on the publike Faith, and by the Mediation of the King of France, and the Lord Protector of England, &amp;c. may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, and kept: and that our Subjects, (exhausted to the very last extremity) may not any longer be oppressed by contributions, entertainings, and quarterings of Souldiers, but that the Armies may be so far drawn off, that both we and themselves may effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and at length, enjoy the fruits of the said concluded, ratified Peace; since our Subjects were never so hard put to it, as at present, no not during the fiercest of the Wars: Not considering, that we on our parts, by the delivery of the <hi>Provinces</hi> of <hi>Shonen,</hi> and <hi>Bleking,</hi> with all the strong places therein, the <hi>Domains</hi> of <hi>Bahu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theim,</hi> (both which Territories contain the one half of the Limits of our Kingdom of <hi>Norway.</hi> Moreover by our evacuation of <hi>Yem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pterland,</hi> and our quitting the Fortress of <hi>Bremerfeurd,</hi> our deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the 2000 <hi>horse,</hi> our satisfying and contenting Duke <hi>Frederick of Sleswigh, Holstein, and Gottorp,</hi> and have complyed in full with whatsoever was contained in the Articles of Peace. Moreover be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides all that, to preserve and continue Peace, and quietness, we have made over to the <hi>King of Sweden the Island of Ween,</hi> although the same hath no dependency at all upon the Province of <hi>Shonen.</hi> Whereas to the contrary, on the behalf of the said King, the <hi>Isles of Funen and Langland,</hi> all <hi>Yutland,</hi> with the Principalities of <hi>Holstein, Sles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wigh,</hi> have not been restored unto us, but are at this very present time, most heavily, and sadly oppressed, and burned, by the whole body of the <hi>Swedish Field-Army,</hi> whereby several of the Inhabitants of the said parts have been constrained to desert their habitations, and livings, and to let them go to ruine, and those who are remained in their said dwellings, are ready to despair, and must needs fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heavy oppressures, and burthens of the War; in regard whereof we do earnestly intreat the <hi>said King</hi> to take to heart the great desolation, oppression, and sad complaints of the Countrie People, and according to the Articles of Peace, to give orders for the marching away of those Forces, which were to depart on the <hi>first of May,</hi> without any further delay; that so our poor distressed subjects might at length enjoy Peace, and quietness.</p>
               <p>We can easily conjecture (as it hath also been told us by others)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119122:34"/> that the <hi>King of Sweden</hi> will lay the fault on us, as if the Treaties had been so long time here protracted, and not as yet brought to any conclusion; Therefore we have deemed it fitting, to adde hereunto whatsoever hath been negotiated, from the beginning to this very time, for your better instruction, that you may be the better provided <hi>to answer this or that objection.</hi> As concerning the <hi>Guinea satisfaction,</hi> we have proffered more then is reasonable; and we are ready to do as much on the remaining undebated particulars: wherefore the <hi>Swedes</hi> are not to be excused, in letting their whole army lye thus heavy upon us, after the ratification of the Peace. Despoyling our Dominions to the uttermost, and beyond all sence, or consideration, bereaving us of all our Powers, and Revenues together.</p>
               <p>We are also advertised, that the King of Sweden hath harboured some Jealousies concerning the <hi>Dutch Ambassadors, the Lord Beunings</hi> intimacy with us, and hath thereon taken an impression, that we are entred upon some private Treaty <hi>to the prejudice of the Crown of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> Hereupon you may assure his <hi>Majestie</hi> with all confidence, and in truth, that we never harboured such a thought, only have confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him on the continuing, and hastning of the Peace.</p>
               <p>'And what more you shall finde fitting to say, or alleadg, conducing to the drawing away of the Souldiery, we leave that to your fidelity, and we have likewise commanded our <hi>Councellors,</hi> and our <hi>Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary General</hi> at <hi>Gluckstadt,</hi> to communicate unto you those aggrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances which they have there suffered, and to propound unto you the best wayes, whereby they may be remedied, that you may joyntly exhibit them to the <hi>King of Sweden,</hi> and seek their redress, and you shall be very urgent, and pressing, that you may be dispatched, as to the several Particulars, with full, and absolute resolves, not regarding your staying by the <hi>King of Swedens Person,</hi> in case there shall be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to give an account of any thing to Us; we have thought good to send you, only as a <hi>Deputy</hi> or <hi>Envoy,</hi> to avoid Ceremonies, not doubting but our Letters will give you Credence enough. But, and if at your being at <hi>Gottorp,</hi> there shall be any proposals made, how and in what manner our <hi>Dukedoms</hi> may separatly be exempted from those burdens, you shall accept of the same, only to advise thereon, and shall sound the <hi>Dukes</hi> minde, and resolutions therein; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119122:35"/> the <hi>Dukedom of Holstein</hi> is a Province of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and a member thereof, it cannot (according to the <hi>Emperial and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Constitutions</hi>) be oppressed, or burdened, without any reason at all, or occasion given, by a <hi>Forreigne Prince.</hi> As to the rest we r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mit it to your judicious Capacity, and remain, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>O</hi> Article the First.</head>
               <p>IN the first place there shall be betwixt <hi>both King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir Successors, K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Countries, Servants, Subjects, and Inhabitants of, and in Denmark, Norway, and Sweden, a firm, perpetual, and irrevo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able Peace, in such a manner, as that all misunderstandings, dissentions, strifes, quarrels, enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Wars, and Hostilities shall cease, and be ended, as also all those things which have passed on both sides, as well before, as during this war, shall (by vertue of a general amnesty, or act of oblivion, comprizing all whatsoever is is past) be forgotten, and no more spoken of, or remembred; but to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there shall be a firm amity, confidence, union, and true neighbourhood setled; in such a manner, as that both parties shall endeavor to advance, and promote the others good, and welfare, both in words, and deeds, as if it were their own, and shall prevent, and hinder all whatsoever may prove prejudicial, and hurtful to each others Persons, Governments, Kingdoms, Countreys, and Subjects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>P</hi> Extract of the Swedish Articles of Peace with the King of Denmark, at the end of the <hi>28.</hi> article, translated out of the Swedish Tongue.</head>
               <p>FOr the better manifestation, and the greater assurance, that all whatsoever is before specified, is thus in the several points thereof, by us done, agreed unto, and concluded upon, and that on the behalf of his Majesty our <hi>most gracious King, and the Crown of Sweden,</hi> it shall be faithfully, inviolably kept, and performed, as also that the Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof shall by Us be exhibited, and delivered in, at a certain appointed day; We have subscribed the same with our own hand writings, and thereunto have applyed our Seals. Desiring moreover, both <hi>the Ordinary Ambassador of the King of France,</hi> and <hi>the Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Envoy of his Highness the Lord Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland</hi> (as having been Mediators in this Peace) to be pleased for the better confirmation, and more essential testimony of the same, to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe, and seal it joyntly with us. Done at <hi>Rotschilt</hi> on the 26. of <hi>Febr. in the Year of our Lord</hi> 1658. Signed thus, <hi>Le Chevalier Terlon, Corfitz Earl of Ʋlefelt, Philip Meadow, Steno Bielke.</hi> Each with a Seal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119122:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>